Action Words

Actions provide a means of asynchronous processing involving message-passing that is lighter-weight than tasks as all computation takes place within a single task and there is none of the complexities of dealing with multiprocessing (except when handling other tasks adding actions to or removing actions from a scheduler that is currently running within a given task, which are minimal in impact). Individual actions do not have their own stacks but rather share the stacks of their parent task.

Message-passing between actions is synchronous; a given action is halted when it is waiting to receive a message or when it is waiting for the message it has sent to be received. Messages can be of any size, and are stored in a buffer provided by the sending task and copied into a buffer provided by the receiving task when received. Note that no order is guaranteed with regard to message-passing, but messages are guaranteed to be eventually received. Note that actions may only send messages to actions within the same schedule; otherwise they will be ignored. Also, if an action is waiting to send a message and that other message is removed from the schedule, the first action is unblocked.

Schedules may be run in any task, may have actions added to or removed from them at any time, and may be stopped safely at any time (the current action’s execution is completed before the schedule stops executing). One note is that a schedule may not be run while it is already running, whether from within the same task or from within a different task.

action

These words are in the module action.

current-schedule

( – schedule )

Get the current schedule.

current-action

( – action )

Get the current action.

current-data

( – data )

Get the current action’s data.

action-schedule@

( action – schedule )

Get the schedule of an action.

action-data@

( action – data )

Get the data of an action.

in-schedule?

( action – flag )

Get whether an action is in a schedule.

schedule-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of a schedule in bytes.

action-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of an action in bytes.

init-schedule

( addr – )

Initialize a schedule at the address addr.

init-action

( data xt addr – )

Initialize an action at the address addr with the initial execution token xt and the data data

add-action

( schedule action – )

Add an action action to schedule schedule. This may be done at any time, including while the schedule is executing.

remove-action

( schedule action – )

Remove an action action from schedule schedule. This may be done at any time, including while the schedule is executing.

send-action

( send-xt addr bytes dest-action – )

Send a message in a buffer at addr of size bytes to action dest-action and set the send execution token to be called once the message is sent or message-sending fails to send-xt. send-xt has the signature ( – ). Sending a message is synchronous; the current action will not execute until either the message is received or the message becomes unable to be sent. dest-action must be in the current schedule or otherwise this routine is a no-op. Sending a message must be done within an executing schedule; messages may not be sent outside of a schedule. Only one message may be sent before control returns to the scheduler; to send multiple messages, send them within subsequent send-xts.

send-action-fail

( send-xt fail-xt addr bytes dest-action – )

Send with failure-handling a message in a buffer at addr of size bytes to action dest-action, set the send execution token to be called once the message is sent to send-xt, and set the failure execution token to be called if message-sending fails to fail-xt. send-xt and fail-xt have the signature ( – ). Sending a message is synchronous; the current action will not execute until either the message is received or the message becomes unable to be sent. dest-action must be in the current schedule or otherwise this routine is a no-op. Sending a message must be done within an executing schedule; messages may not be sent outside of a schedule. Only one message may be sent before control returns to the scheduler; to send multiple messages, send them within subsequent send-xts.

send-action-timeout

( send-xt fail-xt addr bytes dest-action timeout-ticks – )

Send with failure and timeoout-handling a message in a buffer at addr of size bytes to action dest-action with a timeout of timeout-ticks, set the send execution token to be called once the message is sent to send-xt, and set the failure/timeout execution token to be called if message-sending fails to fail-xt. send-xt and fail-xt have the signature ( – ). Sending a message is synchronous; the current action will not execute until either the message is received, the message becomes unable to be sent, or the timeout is reached. dest-action must be in the current schedule or otherwise this routine is a no-op. Sending a message must be done within an executing schedule; messages may not be sent outside of a schedule. Only one message may be sent before control returns to the scheduler; to send multiple messages, send them within subsequent send-xts.

recv-action

( recv-xt addr bytes – )

Receive a message sent to the current action into a buffer at addr of size bytes and set the receive execution token to recv-xt. recv-xt has the signature ( addr bytes src-action – ) where addr is the same addr of the buffer provided earlier, bytes is the actual size of the message received or the size of the buffer, whichever is smaller, and src-action is the source action which sent the message received. Receiving messages is synchronous; the current action will not execute until a message is received. Note that only messages sent from other actions in the same schedule may be received.

recv-action-timeout

( recv-xt timeout-xt addr bytes timeout-ticks – )

Receive a message sent to the current action into a buffer at addr of size bytes and set the receive execution token to recv-xt and the timeout execution token to timeout-xt. recv-xt has the signature ( addr bytes src-action – ) where addr is the same addr of the buffer provided earlier, bytes is the actual size of the message received or the size of the buffer, whichever is smaller, and src-action is the source action which sent the message received. Receiving messages is synchronous; the current action will not execute until either a message is received or timeout-ticks elapses, where then execution will resume at timeout-xt rather than at recv-xt as it would were a message received. Note that only messages sent from other actions in the same schedule may be received.

delay-action

( resume-xt systick-start systick-delay – )

Delay the current action to a time starting from systick-start ticks with a delay of systick-delay ticks and set the resume execution token to resume-xt.

yield-action

( resume-xt – )

Yield the current action and set the resume execution token to resume-xt.

run-schedule

( schedule – )

Run the schedule schedule in the current task. Note that this may not be done if the schedule is already running in any task.

stop-schedule

( schedule – )

Stop the schedule schedule safely, allowing it to finish executing its current action before stopping.

x-already-in-schedule

( – )

Action is already in schedule exception.

x-not-in-schedule

( – )

Action is not in a schedule exception.

x-schedule-already-running

( – )

Schedule is already running exception.

x-operation-set

( – )

Operation is already set for current action exception.

Action Pool words

Action pools provide a means allocating and reusing action scheduler actions out of a fixed sized pool. Actions that have not been added to a schedule or which have been removed from a schedule, whether manually or automatically (e.g. through failing to specify a continuation or through raising an uncaught exception) are considered free for allocation. Actions’ initial execution tokens and data are assigned at the time that they are added to an action, unlike when manually initializing actions and adding them to schedules where the two are separate operations.

action-pool

The following words are in action-pool:

x-no-action-available

( – )

Exception raised if one attempts to allocate a action from a action pool and no actions are available.

add-action-from-pool

( schedule dat xt action-pool – action )

Initalize a action from a action pool with the initial execution token xt and data data, if a action is available, or raise x-no-action-available if no actions are available. The action is then added to the schedule schedule and is returned.

action-pool-free

( action-pool – count )

Get the number of free actions in a action pool.

init-action-pool

( count addr – )

Initialize a action pool at addr, with count actions. These actions are free initially to be initialized and added to a schedule with add-action-from-pool.

action-pool-size

( count – bytes )

Get the size taken up by a action pool with count actions; this size should be used for alloting the block of memory to be passed to init-action-pool

Software Alarm Words

Software alarms are time-based alarms that can be registered with an alarm task, which may be either automatically or explicitly created. Alarm tasks are tasks for which a list of alarms are associated which execute said alarms when the alarms’ times expire. At bootup no alarm tasks are created, but if a default alarm task has not been created at the time that an alarm is first set using a default alarm task, a default alarm task is automatically created with a dictionary size of 320 bytes, a data stack size of 128 bytes, a return stack size of 512 bytes, and a core (relevant to operation on the RP2040) of 0. If a different default alarm task configuration is desired, init-default-alarm-task is to be used.

Alarms are created with a set delay after a start time, which can be set for convenience to the current time, after which they are triggered, calling their specified execution token, even if the trigger time was in the past when they were created. All times are measured in ticks, which are normally 100 microsecond intervals, with the current time corresponding to systick::systick-counter. Alarms are one-shot - they must always be manually set again after they are triggered. Alarms also have a set priority; an alarm task takes on the maximum of all the priorities of the currently active alarms associated with it. Alarms have an associated data value, to eliminate the memory cost and complexity of creating a closure for them in many cases. Their execution token has the signature ( data alarm – ) for convenience for accessing their associated data and resetting themselves, for repeated alarms.

Alarms may be dynamically set and unset; note, however, that it is not safe to set an alarm that has already been set and which has not been triggered yet, as setting an alarm assumes that it is uninitialized and initializes it in the process. It is safe to set an alarm which has either been triggered or manually unset again. It is also safe to unset an alarm which has previously been set which has already been triggered or has previously been unset.

alarm

The alarm module contains the following words:

alarm-size

( – bytes )

This returns the size of an alarm structure in bytes.

alarm-task-size

( – bytes )

This returns the size of an alarm task structure in bytes, not including the size of the associated task which is created when the alarm task structure is initialize.

init-alarm-task

( dict-size stack-size rstack-size core alarm-task – )

Initialize an alarm task alarm-task, of size alarm-task-size, with a dictionary size of dict-size bytes, a data stack size of stack-size bytes, a return stack size of rstack-size, a core of core (on non-RP2040 platforms this must be 0). This will create a task for the alarm task with the name alarm.

init-default-alarm-task

( dict-size stack-size rstack-size core – )

Initialize a default alarm task, with a dictionary size of dict-size bytes, a data stack size of stack-size bytes, a return stack size of rstack-size, and a core of core (on non-RP2040 platforms this must be 0). If a default alarm task has already been initialized, whether explicitly through this word or implicitly through calling default-alarm-task@, set-alarm-default, or set-alarm-delay-default, x-default-alarm-task-already-inited will be raised.

default-alarm-task@

( – default-alarm-task )

Get the default alarm task, initializing it (as mentioned above) if it has not already been initialized..

set-alarm

( ticks-delay ticks-start priority data xt alarm alarm-task – )

Set (and initialize) an alarm alarm for alarm-task alarm-task to execute xt with data data with priority priority at ticks-delay (or greater) ticks after ticks-start. It is assumed that alarm is not currently set, where if it is undefined results will occur.

set-alarm-default

( ticks-delay ticks-start priority data xt alarm – )

Set (and initialize) an alarm alarm for the default alarm task, which will be initialized as mentioned above if not already initialized, to execute xt with data data with priority priority at ticks-delay (or greater) ticks after ticks-start. It is assumed that alarm is not currently set, where if it is undefined results will occur.

set-alarm-delay

( ticks-delay priority data xt alarm alarm-task – )

Set (and initialize) an alarm alarm for alarm-task alarm-task to execute xt with data data with priority priority at ticks-delay (or greater) ticks after the current value of systick::systick-counter. It is assumed that alarm is not currently set, where if it is undefined results will occur.

set-alarm-delay-default

( ticks-delay priority data xt alarm – )

Set (and initialize) an alarm alarm for the default alarm task, which will be initialized as mentioned above if not already initialized, to execute xt with data data with priority priority at ticks-delay (or greater) ticks after the current value of systick::systick-counter. It is assumed that alarm is not currently set, where if it is undefined results will occur.

unset-alarm

( alarm – )

Unset an alarm that has been previously set (and thus initialized). This is safe even if said alarm has previously been triggered or otherwise unset.

x-default-alarm-task-already-inited

( – )

Default alarm task already initialized exception.

Channel Words

A channel is a monodirectional means of communicating data, as arbitrary-sized blocks of data, between two or more different tasks. Channels form a fixed-size queue onto which data is sent on one end and data is received on the other. Any task which attempts to send data on a full channel, or receive data on an empty channel, will be suspended until either data is received from the channel, or data is sent to the channel, respectively, unless non-blocking operations are used, where then x-would-block (declared in task) is raised instead of blocking.

Channels can be created anywhere in memory; they are not dependent upon any allocation mechanism. Therefore they can be put into alloted memory in the dictionary or into allocated memory in the heap. Note that the size of a channel for a given element size and element count may be calculated with chan-size.

chan

The following words are in chan:

x-chan-closed

( – )

Channel closed exception. Raised on attempting to send to a closed channel or when trying to receive on an empty closed channel.

chan-full?

( chan – flag )

Get whether a channel is full.

chan-empty?

( chan – flag )

Get whether a channel is empty.

chan-size

( element-bytes element-count – total-bytes )

Get the size in memory for a channel with a specified element size in bytes and element count.

init-chan

( element-bytes element-count addr – )

Initialize a channel starting at the specified address with the element size and element count. The element-bytes and element-count should be the same as when they were passed to chan-size when alloting or allocating the memory whose starting address is passed in.

close-chan

( chan – )

Close a channel. Raise x-chan-closed for all pending sending tasks or for all pending receiving tasks if the channel is empty.

reopen-chan

( chan – )

Reopen a channel.

chan-closed?

( chan – closed )

Get whether a channel is closed.

send-chan

( addr bytes chan – )

Send message with a buffer as a payload over a channel. Block until another task receives the message if the channel is full. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the buffer size of the channel is smaller than the data provided, and padded with zeros if it is larger. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

recv-chan

( addr bytes chan – recv-bytes )

Receive message into a buffer from a channel. Block until another task sends a message if the channel is empty. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-chan

( addr bytes chan – addr peek-bytes )

Peek the oldest message into a buffer from a channel, without popping it from the channel’s queue. Block until another task sends a message if the channel is empty. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-chan

( chan – )

Skip the most oldest message in a channel. Block until another task sends a message if the channel is empty. Note that no copying takes place, making this faster than receiving a message. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

send-chan-no-block

( addr bytes chan – )

Send message with a buffer as a payload over a channel. If the channel is full, x-would-block is raised. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the buffer size of the channel is smaller than the data provided, and padded with zeros if it is larger. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

recv-chan-no-block

( addr bytes chan – recv-bytes )

Receive message into a buffer from a channel. If the channel is empty, x-would-block is raised. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-chan-no-block

( addr bytes chan – addr peek-bytes )

Peek the oldest message into a buffer from a channel, without popping it from the channel’s queue. If the channel is empty, x-would-block is raised. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-chan-no-block

( chan – )

Skip the most oldest message in a channel. If the channel is empty, x-would-block is raised. Note that no copying takes place, making this faster than receiving a message. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

Pico clock control words

These words allow the RP2040/RP2350 system clock (normally 125 MHz on the RP2040, 150 MHz on the RP2350) to be changed. This is sometimes desirable, for example if it is necessary to run PIO operations at an integer multiple of 10 MHz on an RP2040. In that case, the system clock can be changed to 120 MHz. Other values are allowed, subject to the limitations outlined in the PLL chapter of the RP2040 and RP2350 data sheets.

forth

The following words are built into the kernel:

xosc-frequency

( – u )

Returns the crystal oscillator frequency in Hz. This is set at built time; currently only 12 MHz is supported.

sysclk

( – addr )

Get the address of the system clock frequency in Hz. This is initialized to 125 MHz on the RP2040, or 150 MHz on the RP2350, and will be changed to the new value by set-sysclk.

clocks

The following words are in clocks:

set-sysclk

( refdiv fbdiv pdiv1 pdiv2 – )

This changes the RP2040/RP2350 system clock (“SYSCLK”) using the PLL parameters given. The resulting system clock frequency is xosc-frequency refdiv / fbdiv * pdiv1 / pdiv2 /. Refer to the RP2040 data sheet for the rules on which values are allowed and what restrictions apply on the internally generated frequencies that result. This sets an upper limit of a 200 MHz system clock on the RP2040 and a 150 MHz system clock on the RP2350, per their current ratings.

Since SYSCLK is the clock source for the UART, I2C, and SPI subsystems, if this word is used to change the SYSCLK frequency, those interfaces will run at a different rate than before. The appropriate rate setting words (uart-baud!, i2c-clock!, or spi-baud!) should be called after any call to set-sysclk to reload the devices with the divider values needed for the updated system clock frequency.

set-sysclk-overclock

( refdiv fbdiv pdiv1 pdiv2 – )

This word is like set-sysclk but it does not set an upper limit on the resulting system clock. Use with care! An inappropriate setting can brick your RP2040/RP2350, and even speeds that the RP2350/RP2350 itself can tolerate may be too fast for the Quad SPI flash!

x-bad-refdiv

( – )

Exception for reference divider value out of range.

x-bad-fbdiv

( – )

Exception for VCO feedback divider value out of range.

x-bad-postdiv1

( – )

Exception for post divider 1 value out of range.

x-bad-postdiv2

( – )

Exception for post divider 2 value out of range.

x-bad-refclk

( – )

Exception for VCO refclock frequency out of range.

x-bad-vcofreq

( – )

Exception for VCO frequency out of range.

x-bad-sysclk

( – )

Exception for sysclk frequency out of range.

Closures

Closures in zeptoforth involve binding an execution token with a single-cell, double-cell, or multi-cell value at a specified, arbitrary address in RAM; this address will then serve as an execution token itself which, when executed, pushes the bound value onto the stack and then execute the bound execution token. The only requirement for the address specified is that it is halfword-aligned.

closure

The closure module contains the following words:

closure-size

( – bytes )

The size of a single-cell closure in bytes.

2closure-size

( – bytes )

The size of a double-cell closure in bytes.

nclosure-size

( count – bytes )

The size of a multi-cell closure containing count values in bytes.

bind

( x addr xt – )

Bind the execution token xt to single-cell value x at address addr in RAM, which will serve as a new execution token. closure-size bytes must be available at addr. When addr is executed as an execution token, the single-cell value x will be pushed onto the stack and then the execution token xt will be executed. addr can be arbitrarily reused and can be at any address in RAM.

2bind

( d addr xt – )

Bind the execution token xt to double-cell data d at address addr in RAM, which will serve as a new execution token. 2closure-size bytes must be available at addr. When addr is executed as an execution token, the double-cell value x will be pushed onto the stack and then the execution token xt will be executed. addr can be arbitrarily reused and can be at any address in RAM.

nbind

( xn … x0 count addr xt – )

Bind the execution token xt to count multiple values xn through x0 at address addr in RAM, which will serve as a new execution token. nclosure-size (with count specified) bytes must be available at addr. When addr is executed as an execution token, multiple values xn through x0 will be pushed onto the stack and then the execution token xt will be executed. addr can be arbitrarily reused and can be at any address in RAM.

with-closure

( ? x bound-xt scope-xt – ? ) scope-xt: ( ? closure-xt – ? )

Create a closure binding the execution token bound-xt to single-cell data x in the current task’s dictionary, place it on the data stack, and execute scope-xt. When the closure is executed, x will be pushed onto the data stack and bound-xt will be executed. This closure is valid only within the scope of scope-xt, and will be de-alloted from the dictionary after it completes executing or if an exception is raised within it, after which it will re-raise said exception.

with-2closure

( ? d bound-xt scope-xt – ? ) scope-xt: ( ? closure-xt – ? )

Create a closure binding the execution token bound-xt to double-cell data d in the current task’s dictionary, place it on the data stack, and execute scope-xt. When the closure is executed, d will be pushed onto the data stack and bound-xt will be executed. This closure is valid only within the scope of scope-xt, and will be de-alloted from the dictionary after it completes executing or if an exception is raised within it, after which it will re-raise said exception.

with-nclosure

( ? xn … x0 count bound-xt scope-xt – ? ) scope-xt: ( ? closure-xt – ? )

Create a closure binding the execution token bound-xt to multi-cell data xn … x0 consisting of count cells in the current task’s dictionary, place it on the data stack, and execute scope-xt. When the closure is executed, xn … x0 will be pushed onto the data stack and bound-xt will be executed. This closure is valid only within the scope of scope-xt, and will be de-alloted from the dictionary after it completes executing or if an exception is raised within it, after which it will re-raise said exception.

ANS Forth / Forth 2012 Compatibility Words

This is a collection of assorted words added for compatibility with ANS Forth and Forth 2012. Because there may be conflicts with existing words, particularly in the case of find, these words are placed in a compat module from which they may be imported.

One important note is that when this is done within the default module, the word find provided by this module will be shadowed by the existing find word in the forth module; in this case one will have to either refer to it as compat::find or shadow the find in the forth module with:

: find compat::find ;

compat

The compat module contains the following words:

word

( delim “word” – c-addr )

Parse a word delimited by a given character; note that this is not reentrant because the returned counted string is stored in a single global buffer; for new code TOKEN / PARSE-NAME is recommended when possible. Also, this word does not properly handle all sorts of whitespace, such as tabs and values less than $20.

find

( c-addr – c-addr 0 | xt 1 | xt -1 )

Find a word’s xt and whether it is immediate (signaled by 1) or non-immediate (signaled by 0)

cmove

( c-addr1 c-addr2 u – )

Implement the traditional Forth string copying word CMOVE - for new code using MOVE is recommended.

cmove>

( c-add1 c-addr2 u – )

Implement the traditional Forth string copying word CMOVE> - for new code using MOVE is recommended.

within

( test low high – flag )

Determine whether a value is between ‘low’, inclusive, and ‘high’, exclusive.

>number

( D: acc c-addr u – acc’ c-addr’ u’ )

Parse a number in a string ‘c-addr u’ with an accumulator initialized as a double-cell value ‘acc’ using the base stored in BASE

compare

( c-addr1 u1 c-addr2 u2 – n )

Compare two strings for both content and length using the numeric values of bytes compared within and shorter common length.

erase

( c-addr u – )

Fill a buffer with zero bytes.

parse-name

( “token” – c-addr u )

Parse a single token from the input.

u.r

( u width – )

Output a right-justified unsigned value in a specified field width; note that if the value is wider than the specified field width the whole value will be output but no padding spaces will be added.

holds

( c-addr u – )

Add multiple characters to <# # #> numeric formatting.

n>r

( xn .. x1 N – ; R: – x1 .. xn n )

Transfer N items and count to the return stack.

nr>

( – xn .. x1 N ; R: x1 .. xn N – )

Pull N items and count off the return stack.

abort"

( “message” – ) ( Runtime: flag – )

Raise an exception that displays a message and a following newline if the value on the stack at runtime is non-zero.

Core Lock Words

Core locks provide a mutual exclusion mechanism between cores while allowing code executing on the same core to access the protected resource in a nested fashion. This is significant if one needs to protect access to a resource within a critical section on a single core, but one needs to ensure the ability to access that resource within an interrupt handler executing within the same resource. Unlike hardwære spinlocks such as that provided by the RP2040 core locks do not occupy any additional hardware resources, and do not require either some sort of allocation mechanism or a fixed set of pre-allocated hardware resources.

core-lock

The following words are in core-lock:

core-lock-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of a core lock in bytes.

init-core-lock

( addr – )

Initialize a core lock starting at the specified address addr; note that it must be core-lock-size bytes in size.

claim-core-lock

( core-lock – )

Claim a core lock core-lock for the current core. If it is already claimed for a core other than the current core, relinquish control of the current core and try again later repeatly until claiming core-lock is successful. If, when claimed for the current core it had already been claimed for the current core, increment a nested claim counter. Note that this is not safe to execute within an interrupt handler.

claim-core-lock-spin

( core-lock – )

Claim a core lock core-lock for the current core. If it is already claimed for a core other than the current core, spin until it is no longer claimed by any core other the current one, and then claim it. If, when claimed for the current core it had already been claimed for the current core, increment a nested claim counter. Note that this is strictly-speaking safe to execute within an interrupt handler, but that is only advisable if core-lock is only claimed for very short periods of time, because it will cause the interrupt handler to wait until it cain claim corelock.

claim-core-lock-timeout

( core-lock – )

Claim a core lock core-lock for the current core. If it is already claimed for a core other than the current core, relinquish control of the current core and try again later repeatly until claiming core-lock is successful or the current timeout is reached, where then x-timed-out is raised. If, when claimed for the current core it had already been claimed for the current core, increment a nested claim counter. Note that this is not safe to execute within an interrupt handler.

release-core-lock

( core-lock – )

Release a core lock core-lock, decrementing its nested claim counter until it reaches zero. If all previous claims have been balanced, the core-lock may now be claimed by a task on another core.

with-core-lock

( xt core-lock – )

Execute an execution token xt with a given core lock core-lock claimed while it executes, releasing it afterwards. If an exception is raised by xt, release core-lock and then re-raise the exception. Note that this uses the mechanism implemented in claim-core-lock, with all of its associated caveats.

with-core-lock-spin

( xt core-lock – )

Execute an execution token xt with a given core lock core-lock claimed while it executes, releasing it afterwards. If an exception is raised by xt, release core-lock and then re-raise the exception. Note that this uses the mechanism implemented in claim-core-lock-spin, with all the associated caveats.

DMA support

There exists support for the DMA controller on the RP2040. There exist 12 DMA channels, 64 DREQ’s/TREQ’s, and 4 DMA timers. Register to register, buffer to register, register to buffer, and buffer to buffer transfers are supported; the main difference between registers and buffers is that buffers’ addresses are updated with each transfer while registers’ addresses are not. Transfer units of size 1 byte, 2 bytes, and 4 bytes are supported. DREQ’s and TREQ’s are used for synchronizing transfers with other peripherals.

There also exists a global DMA pool to simplify dynamically allocating and freeing DMA channels. It is recommended that one use this rather than manually selecting DMA channels.

dma

The dma module contains the following words:

x-out-of-range-dma-channel

( – )

Out of range DMA index exception.

x-out-of-range-treq

( – )

Out of range transfer request exception.

x-out-of-range-timer

( – )

Out of range timer exception.

x-invalid-transfer-size

( – )

Invalid transfer size exception.

x-out-of-range-timer-value

( – )

Out of range timer dividend or divisor

DREQ_PIO_TX

( sm pio – dreq )

PIO TX DREQ for pio block state machine sm transmit.

DREQ_PIO_RX

( sm pio – dreq )

PIO RX DREQ for pio block state machine sm receive.

DREQ_SPI_TX

( spi – dreq )

SPI TX DREQ for spi peripheral transmit.

DREQ_SPI_RX

( spi – dreq )

SPI RX DREQ for spi peripheral receive.

DREQ_UART_TX

( uart – dreq )

UART TX DREQ for uart peripheral transmit.

DREQ_UART_RX

( uart – dreq )

UART RX DREQ for uart peripheral receive.

DREQ_PWM_WRAP

( pwm – dreq )

PWM DREQ for pwm slice.

DREQ_I2C_TX

( i2c – dreq )

I2C TX DREQ for i2c peripheral transmit.

DREQ_I2C_RX

( i2c – dreq )

I2C RX DREQ for i2c peripheral receive.

DREQ_ADC

( – dreq )

ADC DREQ.

DREQ_XIP_STREAM

( – dreq )

XIP STREAM DREQ.

DREQ_XIP_SSITX

( – dreq )

XIP SSITX DREQ (rp2040 only).

DREQ_XIP_SSIRX

( – dreq )

XIP SSIRX DREQ (rp2040 only).

DREQ_XIP_QMITX

( – dreq )

XIP QMITX DREQ (rp2350 only).

DREQ_XIP_QMIRX

( – dreq )

XIP QMIRX DREQ (rp2350 only).

DREQ_HSTX

( – dreq )

HSTX DREQ (rp2350 only).

DREQ_CORESIGHT

( – dreq )

Coresight DREQ (rp2350 only).

DREQ_SHA256

( – dreq )

SHA256 DREQ (rp2350 only).

TREQ_TIMER

( timer – treq )

DMA timer timer, from 0 to 3, as TREQ.

TREQ_UNPACED

( – treq )

Unpaced transfer TREQ.

TRANS_COUNT_MODE_NORMAL

( count – count’ )

Set a transfer count to be normal (rp2350 only).

TRANS_COUNT_MODE_TRIGGER_SELF

( count – count’ )

Set a transfer count to be trigger-self (rp2350 only).

TRANS_COUNT_MODE_ENDLESS

( count – count’ )

Set a transfer count to be endless (rp2350 only).

REGISTER_READ

( – mode )

Register source mode

REGISTER_WRITE

( – mode )

Register destination mode

INCR_BUFFER_READ

( – mode )

Incrementing buffer source mode

INCR_BUFFER_WRITE

( – mode )

Incrementing buffer destination mode

DECR_BUFFER_READ

( – mode )

Decrementing buffer source mode (rp2350 only)

DECR_BUFFER_WRITE

( – mode )

Decrementing buffer destination mode (rp2350 only)

INCR_RING_BUFFER_READ

( low-ring-bits – mode )

Incrementing ring buffer source mode for a given number of low bits in an address

INCR_RING_BUFFER_WRITE

( low-ring-bits – mode )

Incrementing ring buffer destination mode for a given number of low bits in an addres

DECR_RING_BUFFER_READ

( low-ring-bits – mode )

Decrementing ring buffer source mode for a given number of low bits in an address (rp2350 only)

DECR_RING_BUFFER_WRITE

( low-ring-bits – mode )

Decrementing ring buffer destination mode for a given number of low bits in an addres (rp2350 only)

start-dma

( src dest src-mode dest-mode count size treq channel – )

Start transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with starting source address src and starting destination address dest with source mode src-mode and destination mode dest-mode synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

prepare-dma

( src dest src-mode dest-mode count size treq channel – )

Prepare transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with starting source address src and starting destination address dest with source mode src-mode and destination mode dest-mode synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

start-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest src-mode dest-mode count size treq channel – )

Start transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with starting source address src and starting destination address dest with source mode src-mode and destination mode dest-mode synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq chained to DMA channel chain-to.

prepare-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest src-mode dest-mode count size treq channel – )

Prepare transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with starting source address src and starting destination address dest with source mode src-mode and destination mode dest-mode synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq chained to DMA channel chain-to.

start-register>register-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Start register to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

start-register>buffer-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Start register to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

start-buffer>register-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Start buffer to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

start-buffer>buffer-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Start buffer to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

prepare-register>register-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting register to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

prepare-register>buffer-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting register to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

prepare-buffer>register-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting buffer to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

prepare-buffer>buffer-dma

( src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting buffer to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq.

start-register>register-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Start register to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

start-register>buffer-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Start register to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

start-buffer>register-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Start buffer to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

start-buffer>buffer-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Start buffer to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

prepare-register>register-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting register to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

prepare-register>buffer-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting register to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

prepare-buffer>register-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting buffer to register transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

prepare-buffer>buffer-dma-with-chain

( chain-to src dest count size treq channel – )

Prepare without starting buffer to buffer transfer of count units of size bytes on DMA channel with source address src and destination address dest synchronized by DREQ/TREQ treq with chaining to DMA channel chain-to. Note that if channel is the same as chain-to no chaining will take place.

dma-timer!

( dividend divisor timer – )

Set DMA timer clock dividend and divisor.

spin-wait-dma

( channel – )

Spin wait for DMA channel completion

wait-dma

( channel – )

Non-busy wait for DMA channel completion

halt-dma

( channel – )

Halt DMA channel

abort-dma

( channel – )

Abort DMA channel

dma-src-addr@

( channel – addr )

Get DMA channel source address

dma-dest-addr@

( channel – addr )

Get DMA channel destination address

dma-remaining@

( channel – remaining )

Get outstanding bytes transferred

dma-pool

The dma-pool module contains the following words:

x-no-dma-channels-available

( – )

No DMA channels available exception.

x-dma-channel-already-free

( – )

DMA channel is already free.

x-no-dma-timers-available

( – )

No DMA timers available exception.

x-dma-timer-already-free

( – )

DMA timer is already free.

allocate-dma

( – channel )

Allocate a DMA channel.

free-dma

( channel – )

Free a DMA channel

allocate-timer

( – timer )

Allocate a DMA timer.

free-timer

( timer – )

Free a DMA timer

Dynamically-Scoped Variable Words

Dynamically-scoped variables enable the definition of variables with a scope within a called execution token or within all execution inside a given thread except for within scopes in which they are redefined. Note that values of dynamically-scoped variables are specific to individual tasks, and do not exist for the main task on bootup or within new tasks on spawning.

dynamic

The dynamic module contains the following words:

dyn

( “name” – )

This defines a dynamically-scoped single-cell variable with the specified name. Note that this does not give it any value. If this is executed during compilation to flash the defined variable will persist across reboots.

2dyn

( “name” – )

This defines a dynamically-scoped double-cell variable with the specified name. Note that this does not give it any value. If this is executed during compilation to flash the defined variable will persist across reboots.

dyn!

( xt x|xd variable – )

This sets a dynamically-scoped variable variable to x or xd depending on whether it is single-cell or double-cell within the scope defined by the execution token xt within the current task. This temporarily uses space in the current task’s RAM dictionary to store the defined value of variable.

dyn-no-scope!

( x|xd variable – )

This sets a dynamically-scoped variable variable to xt or xd depending on whether it is single-cell or double-cell within the scope defined by all execution after this point within the current task until overridden by another execution of dyn! or dyn-no-scope!. Note that this permanently uses space in the current task’s RAM dictionary to store the defined value of variable; do not use this within implicit compilation.

dyn@

( variable – x|xd )

This gets the current value of a dynamically-scoped variable variable within the current task as x or xd dependingon whether it is single-cell or double-cell.

FAT32 Support

zeptoforth includes FAT32 filesystem support combined with MBR partition table support on devices implementing the <block-dev> class defined in the module block-dev (currently only the <sd> class defined in the module sd). It supports creating files and directories, reading files and directories, writing files and (indirectly) directories, seeking in files, removing files and (empty) directories, and renaming (but currently not moving) files and directories. It also supports parsing paths within filesystems. It supports reading partition table entries from the MBR, and uses these when initializing FAT32 filesystems.

Note that, prior to zeptoforth 1.7.0, files and directories did not need closing; it was merely up to the user to not carry out operations such as removing them and then carrying out other operations on them afterwards. This has changed; now files need to be closed with close-file and directories need to be closed with close-dir, followed by being destroyed with destroy, once one is done with them. Not doing so may result in undefined behavior, particularly if the space they occupied in RAM is reused afterwards.

fat32

The fat32 module contains the following words:

x-sector-size-not-supported

( – )

Sector size exception.

x-fs-version-not-supported

( – )

Filesystem version not supported exception.

x-bad-info-sector

( – )

Bad info sector exception.

x-no-clusters-free

( – )

No clusters free exception.

x-file-name-format

( – )

Unsupported file name format exception.

x-out-of-range-entry

( – )

Out of range directory entry index exception.

x-out-of-range-partition

( – )

Out of range partition index exception.

x-entry-not-found

( – )

Directory entry not found exception.

x-entry-already-exists

( – )

Directory entry already exists exception.

x-entry-not-file

( – )

Directory entry is not a file exception.

x-entry-not-dir

( – )

Directory entry is not a directory exception.

x-dir-is-not-empty

( – )

Directory is not empty exception.

x-forbidden-dir

( – )

Directory name being changed or set is forbidden exception.

x-empty-path

( – )

No file or directory referred to in path within directory exception.

x-invalid-path

( – )

Invalid path exception.

x-not-open

( – )

Attempted to carry out an operation on a file or directory that is not open.

x-shared-file

( – )

Attempted to carry out an operation on a file where the file must only be open once (i.e. truncate a file).

x-open

( – )

Attempted to carry out an operation on a file or directory that is open (i.e. remove a file or directory).

seek-set

( – whence )

Seek from the beginning of a file.

seek-cur

( – whence )

Seek from the current position in a file

seek-end

( – whence )

<mbr>

The master boot record class. This class is used to read a partition entry from for initializing a FAT32 filesystem.

The <mbr> class includes the following constructor:

new

( mbr-device mbr – )

Construct an <mbr> instance with the block device mbr-device.

The <mbr> class includes the following methods:

mbr-valid?

( mbr – valid? )

Is the MBR valid?

partition@

( partition index mbr – )

Read a partition entry, with an index from 0 to 3.

partition!

( partition index mbr – )

Write a partition entry, with an index from 0 to 3.

<partition>

The master boot record partition entry class. This class is used to read partition entries from the MBR partition table for initializing FAT32 filesystems.

The <partition> class includes the following members:

partition-active

( partition – partition-active )

Partition active state.

partition-type

( partition – partition-type )

Partition type.

partition-first-sector

( partition – partition-first-sector )

Partition first sector index.

partition-sectors

( partition – partition-sectors )

Partition sectors.

partition-active?

( partition – active? )

Is the partition active?

<base-fat32-fs>

( – class )

The base FAT32 filesystem class. This class is not to be instantiated by itself.

The <base-fat32-fs> class includes the following methods, which are implemented by its subclasses:

root-dir@

( dir fs – )

Initialize a root directory of a FAT32 filesystem; the directory object need not be initialized already, but if it is no harm will result.

with-root-path

( c-addr u xt fs ) ( xt: c-addr’ u’ dir – )

Parse a path starting at the root directory of a FAT32 filesystem, and pass the leaf’s name along with a directory object containing that leaf (or which would contain said leaf if it did not exist already) to the passed in xt. Note that said directory object will be destroyed when xt returns.

root-path-exists?

( c-addr u fs – exists? )

Get whether a file or directory exists at the specified path starting at the root directory of a FAT32 filesystem.

flush

( fs – )

Flush any dirty blocks cached by the underlying block device.

<fat32-fs>

( – class )

The FAT32 filesystem class. This class implements <base-fat32-fs>.

The <fat32-fs> class includes the following constructor:

new

( partition device fs – )

Construct an instance of the <fat32-fs> class with block device device and MBR partition entry partition. Note that after executing this the filesystem will be ready for use, and the block device must be in working order at this time.

<fat32-file>

( – class )

The FAT32 file class.

The <fat32-file> class includes the following constructor:

new

( fs file – )

Construct an instance of <fat32-file> with the FAT32 filesystem fs.

The <fat32-file> class includes the following methods:

close-file

( file – )

Close a file.

file-open?

( file – open? )

Get whether a file is open.

read-file

( c-addr u file – bytes )

Read data from a file.

write-file

( c-addr u file – bytes )

Write data to a file.

truncate-file

( file – )

Truncate a file.

seek-file

( offset whence file – )

Seek in a file.

tell-file

( file – offset )

Get the current offset in a file.

file-size@

( file – bytes )

Get the size of a file.

<fat32-dir>

The FAT32 directory class.

The <fat32-dir> class includes the following constructor:

new

( fs file – )

Construct an instance of <fat32-dir> with the FAT32 filesystem fs.

The <fat32-dir> class includes the following methods:

close-dir

( dir – )

Close a directory.

dir-open?

( dir – open? )

Get whether a directory is open.

with-path

( c-addr u xt dir – ) ( xt: c-addr’ u’ dir’ – )

Parse a path starting at a given directory, and pass the leaf’s name along with a directory object containing that leaf (or which would contain said leaf if it did not exist already) to the passed in xt. Note that said directory object will be destroyed when xt returns unless it was the original directory object passed in.

path-exists?

( c-addr u dir – exists? )

Get whether a file or directory exist at the specified path starting at a given directory.

exists?

( c-addr u dir – exists? )

Get whether a directory contains a file or directory of the specified name.

file?

( c-addr u – file? )

Get whether the entry in a directory with the specified name is a file.

dir?

( c-addr u – dir? )

Get whether the entry in a directory with the specified name is a directory.

read-dir

( entry dir – entry-read? )

Read an entry from a directory, and return whether an entry was read.

create-file

( c-addr u new-file dir – )

Create a file. Note that new-file need not be initialized prior to use, but no harm is done if it is.

open-file

( c-addr u opened-file dir – )

Open a file. Note that opened-file need not be initialized prior to use, but no harm is done if it is.

remove-file

( c-addr u dir – )

Remove a file.

create-dir

( c-addr u new-dir dir – )

Create a directory. Note that new-dir need not be initialized prior to use, but no harm is done if it is.

open-dir

( c-addr u opened-dir dir – )

Open a directory. Note that opened-dir need not be initialized prior to use, but no harm is done if it is.

remove-dir

( c-addr u dir – )

Remove a directory.

rename

( new-c-addr new-u c-addr u dir – )

Rename a file or directory.

dir-empty?

( dir – empty? )

Get whether a directory is empty.

<fat32-entry>

( – class )

The FAT32 directory entry class.

The <fat32-entry> class has no constructor.

The <fat32-entry> class has the following members:

short-file-name

( entry – short-file-name-addr )

This member is 8 bytes in size.

The short file name component, padded with spaces.

The first byte can have the special values: $00: final entry in the directory entry table $05: the initial byte is actually $35 $2E: the dot entry $E5: the directory entry has been deleted

short-file-ext

( entry – short-file-ext-addr )

This member is 3 bytes in size.

The short file extension component, padded with spaces.

file-attributes

( entry – file-attributes-addr )

This member is 1 bytes in size.

The file attributes.

There are the following bits: $01: read only $02: hidden $04: system (do not move in the filesystem) $08: volume label $10: subdirectory (subdirectories have a file size of zero) $20: archive $40: device $80: reserved

nt-vfat-case

( entry – nt-vfat-case-addr )

This member is 1 bytes in size.

Windows NT VFAT case information.

create-time-fine

( entry – create-time-fine-addr )

This member is 1 bytes in size.

Create time file resolution, 10 ms increments, from 0 to 199.

create-time-coarse

( entry – create-time-coarse-addr )

This member is 2 bytes in size.

Create time with coarse resolution, 2 s increments.

bits 15-11: hours (0-23) bits 10-5: minutes (0-59) bits 4-0: seconds / 2 (0-29)

create-date

( entry – create-date-addr )

This member is 2 bytes in size.

Create date.

bits 15-9: year (0 = 1980) bits 8-5: month (1-12) bits 4-0: day (1-31)

access-date

( entry – access-date-addr )

This member is 2 bytes in size.

Last access date.

bits 15-9: year (0 = 1980) bits 8-5: month (1-12) bits 4-0: day (1-31)

first-cluster-high

( entry – first-cluster-high-addr )

This member is 2 bytes in size.

High two bytes of the first cluster number.

modify-time-coarse

( entry – modify-time-coarse-addr )

This member is 2 bytes in size.

Last modify time with coarse resolution, 2 s increments.

bits 15-11: hours (0-23) bits 10-5: minutes (0-59) bits 4-0: seconds / 2 (0-29)

modify-date

( entry – modify-date-addr )

This member is 2 bytes in size.

Last modify date.

bits 15-9: year (0 = 1980) bits 8-5: month (1-12) bits 4-0: day (1-31)

first-cluster-low

( entry – first-cluster-low-addr )

This member is 2 bytes in size.

Low two bytes of the first cluster number.

entry-file-size

( entry – entry-file-size-addr )

This member is 4 bytes in size.

The file size; is always 0 for subdirectories and volume labels.

buffer>entry

( addr entry – )

Import a buffer into a directory entry.

entry>buffer

( addr entry – )

Export a directory entry as a buffer.

init-blank-entry

( entry – )

Initialize a blank directory entry.

init-file-entry

( file-size first-cluster c-addr u entry – )

Initialize a file directory entry.

init-dir-entry

( first-cluster c-addr u entry – )

Initialize a subdirectory directory entry.

init-end-entry

( entry – )

Initialize an end directory entry.

mark-entry-deleted

( entry – )

Mark a directory entry as deleted.

entry-deleted?

( entry – deleted? )

Get whether a directory entry has been deleted.

entry-end?

( entry – end? )

Get whether a directory entry is the last in a directory.

entry-file?

( entry – file? )

Get whether a directory entry is for a file.

entry-dir?

( entry – subdir? )

Get whether a directory entry is for a subdirectory.

first-cluster@

( entry – cluster )

Get the first cluster index of a directory entry.

first-cluster!

( cluster entry – )

Set the first cluster index of a directory entry.

file-name!

( c-addr u entry – )

Set the file name of a directory entry, converted from a normal string.

dir-name!

( c-addr u entry – )

Set the directory name of a directory entry, converted from a normal string.

file-name@

( c-addr u entry – c-addr u’ )

Get the file name of a directory entry, converted to a normal string.

create-date-time!

( date-time entry – )

Set the creation date/time of a directory entry, with second resolution.

create-date-time@

( date-time entry – )

Get the creation date/time of a directory entry, with second resolution and day-of-the-week calculation.

modify-date-time!

( date-time entry – )

Set the modification date/time of a directory entry, with two second resolution.

modify-date-time@

( date-time entry – )

Get the modification date/time of a directory entry, with two second resolution and day-of-the-week calculation.

FAT32 Tools

zeptoforth comes with a variety of words for manipulating files and directories in FAT32 filesystems. Directories can be created, listed, removed, and renamed, and files can be created, appended, overwritten, dumped, removed, and renamed.

zeptoforth includes support for including code for execution within FAT32 filesystems. This includes support for handling nested included files, up to a maximum of eight included files. Note that including code is intended to only be done from within the main task, and undefined results may occur if done from within any other task.

fat32-tools

The fat32-tools module contains the following words:

x-fs-not-set

( – )

Current filesystem not set exception.

x-include-stack-overflow

( – )

Include stack overflow exception, raised if the number of nested includes exceeds eight includes.

current-fs!

( fs – )

Set the current FAT32 filesystem. This filesystem is a subclass of <base-fat32-fs> in the fat32 module.

current-fs@

( – fs )

Get the current FAT32 filesystem. This filesystem is a subclass of <base-fat32-fs> in the fat32 module.

init-simple-fat32

( write-through sck-pin tx-pin rx-pin cs-pin spi-device – )

Simple SDHC/SDXC FAT32 card initializer; this creates a SDHC/SDXC card interface and FAT32 filesystem and, if successful, sets it as the current filesystem.

sck-pin, tx-pin, rx-pin, and cs-pin are the clock, transmit, receive, and chip select pins to use. spi-device is the SPI peripheral to use; it must match sck-pin, tx-pin, and rx-pin. write-through is whether to enable write-through; enabling write-through will result in greater data integrity in the case of failures, but slower performance. If write-through is not enabled, manually flushing at opportune moments is highly recommended.

Note that this permanently allots space for the FAT32 filesystem and its support structures in the current task’s RAM dictionary.

load-file

( file – )

Load code from a file in the FAT32 filesystem. Note that the file object will be duplicated in the process. The contents of the file will be echoed to the console as it is evaluated.

included

( path-addr path-u – )

Load code from a file with the specified path in the current include FAT32 filesystem. The contents of the file will be echoed to the console as it is evaluated.

include

( “path” – )

Load code from a file with the specified path as a token in the current include FAT32 filesystem. The contents of the file will be echoed to the console as it is evaluated.

list-dir

( path-addr path-u – )

List a directory at the specified path. Display the file creation date, modification date, and size.

create-file

( data-addr data-u path-addr path-u – )

Create a file at the specified path and write data to it.

create-dir

( path-addr path-u – )

Create a directory at the specified path.

copy-file

( path-addr path-u new-path-addr new-path-u – )

Copy a file from an existing path to a new path.

append-file

( data-addr data-u path-addr path-u – )

Write data to the end of a file at the specified path.

write-file

( data-addr data-u path-addr path-u – )

Overwrite a file at the specified path with data and then truncate it afterwards.

write-file-window

( data-addr data-u offset-u path-addr path-u – )

Write data at an offset to a file at the specified path without truncating it.

list-file

( path-addr path-u – )

List a file at the specified path on the console, converting lone LF characters to CRLF pairs.

list-file-window

( offset-u length-u path-addr path-u – )

List a defined window in a file at the specified path on the console, converting lone LF characters to CRLF pairs.

dump-file

( path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a file at the specified path to the console as hexadecimal bytes plus ASCII.

dump-file-window

( offset-u length-u path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a defined window in a file at the specified path to the console as hexadecimal bytes plus ASCII

dump-file-raw

( path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a file at the specified path to the console as raw data, without processing.

dump-file-raw-window

( offset-u length-u path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a defined window in a file at the specified path to the console as raw data, without processing.

dump-file-ascii

( path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a file at the specified path to the console as ASCII.

dump-file-ascii-window

( offset-u length-u path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a defined window in a file at the specified path to the console as ASCII.

dump-file-halfs

( path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a file at the specified path to the console as hexadecimal halfwords plus ASCII.

dump-file-halfs-window

( offset-u length-u path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a defined window in a file at the specified path to the console as hexadecimal halfwords plus ASCII

dump-file-cells

( path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a file at the specified path to the console as hexadecimal cells plus ASCII.

dump-file-cells-window

( offset-u length-u path-addr path-u – )

Dump the contents of a defined window in a file at the specified path to the console as hexadecimal cells plus ASCII

read-file

( buffer-addr buffer-u offset-u path-addr path-u – read-u )

Read a file at the specified path, from an offset from the start of the file, to a fixed-sized buffer and return the length in bytes actually read.

file-size@

( path-addr path-u – size-u )

Get the size in bytes of a file at the specified path.

exists?

( path-addr path-u – exists? )

Get whether a file or directory exists at the specified path.

remove-file

( path-addr path-u – )

Remove a file at the specified path.

remove-dir

( path-addr path-u – )

Remove a directory at the specified path. Note that it must be empty aside from the . and .. entries.

rename

( path-addr path-u new-name-addr new-name-u – )

Rename a file or directory at the specified path to a new name (not path). Note that files’ and directories’ parent directories cannot be changed with this word.

file?

( path-addr path-u – file? )

Get whether the entry at a specified path is a file.

dir?

( path-addr path-u – dir? )

Get whether the entry at a specified path is a directory.

Rendezvous Channel Words

A rendezvous channel is a monodirectional means of communicating data between two different tasks. Rendezvous channels are not buffered queues; provided another task is listening to a rendezvous channel, sending on a rendezvous channel immediately transfers control to the receiving task and sends the sending task to the end of the scheduling ring. Only a single copy is done when transferring data from the sending task to the receiving task.

Tasks attempting to send on rendezvous channels first check whether there is a queued task waiting to receive on the rendezvous channel; if there are tasks queued to receive, the first task queued is dequeued, the sending task’s buffer is copied into the receiving task’s buffer, and the receiving task is readied. If no tasks are queued to receive, the sending task is queued to send on the rendezvous channel and is blocked, if send-fchan had been called, otherwise task::x-would-block is raised, if send-fchan-no-block had been called.

Tasks attempting to receive on rendezvous channels first check whether there is a queued task waiting to send on the rendezvous channel; if there are tasks queued to send, the first task queued is dequeued, the sending task’s buffer is copied into the receiving task’s buffer, and the sending task is readied. If no tasks are queued to send, the receiving task is queued to receive on the rendezvous channel and is blocked, if recv-fchan had been called, otherwise task::x-would-block is raised, if recv-fchan-no-block had been called.

Both the send queues and receive queues are ordered first by task priority and second by the order in which tasks were added to them, with tasks of higher priority and tasks added earlier coming first.

Rendezvous channels can be created anywhere in memory; they are not dependent upon any allocation mechanism. Therefore they can be put into alloted memory in the dictionary or into allocated memory in the heap.

fchan

The following words are in fchan:

x-fchan-closed

( – )

The rendezvous channel closed exception.

fchan-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of an rendezvous channel in bytes.

init-fchan

( addr – )

Initialize a rendezvous channel starting at the specified address.

close-fchan

( fchan – )

Close a rendezvous channel. Pending sends and receives will be aborted with the exception x-fchan-closed.

reopen-fchan

( fchan – )

Reopen a rendezvous channel.

fchan-closed?

( fchan – closed )

Get whether a rendezvous channel is closed.

send-fchan

( addr bytes fchan – )

Send message with a buffer as a payload over a rendezvous channel. Block until another task receives the message; if a task is already waiting for a message, transfer control to it. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the buffer size of the rendezvous channel is smaller than the data provided, and padded with zeros if it is larger. Note that this must not be called within a critical section.

send-fchan-no-block

( addr bytes fchan – )

Send message with a buffer as a payload over a rendezvous channel. If a task is already waiting for a message, transfer control to it, otherwise raise task::x-would-block. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the buffer size of the rendezvous channel is smaller than the data provided, and padded with zeros if it is larger. Note that this must not be called within a critical section.

recv-fchan

( addr bytes fchan – recv-bytes )

Receive message with a buffer as a payload over a rendezvous channel. Block until another task sends a message. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the rendezvous channel; the number of bytes copied is returned. Note that this must not be called within a critical section.

recv-fchan-no-block

( addr bytes fchan – recv-bytes )

Receive message with a buffer as a payload over a rendezvous channel. If no task is waiting to send a message, raise task::x-would-block. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the rendezvous channel; the number of bytes copied is returned. Note that this must not be called within a critical section.

GPIO Words

A GPIO API is provided for STM32 microcontrollers, with slight variations between individual microcontrollers (primarily in the number of supported GPIO’s, along with internal differences in the registers used by the API). It provides a thin layer over the hardware registers that control GPIO’s, so as to make them more user-friendly while not limiting the programmer’s capabilities.

A GPIO API is also provided for the RP2040; note that this API differs considerably from the GPIO API for STM32 microcontrollers and has no compatiblity with it. It exposes registers for manipulating GPIO input and output and for controlling GPIO interrupts.

These words are in gpio.

STM32 Words

gpio

GPIOA through GPIOK

These are the memory addresses of the spaces for each of the the GPIO’s, from GPIOA to GPIOI on the STM32F407 and STM32L476, from GPIOA to GPIOK on the STM32F746, and from GPIOA to GPIOE as well as GPIOH on the STM32F411.

MODER

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_MODER address.

OTYPER

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_OTYPER address.

OSPEEDR

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_OSPEEDR address.

PUPDR

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_PUPDR address.

IDR

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_IDR address.

ODR

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_ODR address.

BSRR

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_BSRR address.

LCKR

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_LCKR address.

AFRL

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_AFRL address.

AFRH

( gpio-addr – addr )

This takes a base GPIOx address and outputs a GPIOx_AFRH address.

INPUT_MODE

This is the input port mode.

OUTPUT_MODE

This is the output port mode.

ALTERNATE_MODE

This is the alternate function port mode.

ANALOG_MODE

This is the analog port mode.

PUSH_PULL

This is the push-pull output type.

OPEN_DRAIN

This is the open drain output type.

LOW_SPEED

This is the low speed output speed.

MEDIUM_SPEED

This is the medium speed output speed.

HIGH_SPEED

This is the high speed output speed.

VERY_HIGH_SPEED

This is the very high speed output speed.

NO_PULL_UP_PULL_DOWN

This is the no pull up/pull down setting.

PULL_UP

This is the pull up setting.

PULL_DOWN

This is the pull down setting.

gpio-clock-enable

( gpio-addr – )

Enable the clock for the specified GPIO.

gpio-lp-clock-enable

( gpio-addr – )

Enable the low-power clock for the specified GPIO.

gpio-clock-disable

( gpio-addr – )

Disable the clock for the specified GPIO.

gpio-lp-clock-disable

( gpio-addr – )

Disable the low-power clock for the specified GPIO.

gpio-clock-enable?

( gpio-addr – enable )

Get whether the clock for the specified GPIO is enabled.

gpio-lp-clock-enable?

( gpio-addr – enable )

Get whether the low-power clock for the specified GPIO is enabled.

MODER!

( mode pin gpio-addr – )

Set the specified mode for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

OTYPER!

( otype pin gpio-addr – )

Set the specified output type for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

OSPEEDR!

( ospeed pin gpio-addr – )

Set the specified output speed for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

PUPDR!

( pupd pin gpio-addr – )

Set the specified pull up/pull down setting for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

AFRL!

( af pin gpio-addr – )

Set the specified alternate function for the specified pin (from 0 to 7) on the specified GPIO.

AFRH!

( af pin gpio-addr – )

Set the specified alternate function for the specified pin (from 8 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

AFR!

( af pin gpio-addr – )

Set the specified alternate function for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

BS!

( pin gpio-addr – )

Set the output for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO to on.

BR!

( pin gpio-addr – )

Set the output for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO to off.

BSRR!

( output pin gpio-addr – )

Set the output for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO to on or off.

MODER@

( pin gpio-addr – mode )

Get the mode of the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

OTYPER@

( pin gpio-addr – otype )

Get the output type of the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

OSPEEDR@

( pin gpio-addr – ospeed )

Get the output speed of the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

PUPDR@

( pin gpio-addr – pupd )

Get the pull up/pull down setting of the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

AFRL@

( pin gpio-addr – af )

Get the alternate function for the specified pin (from 0 to 7) on the specified GPIO.

AFRH@

( pin gpio-addr – af )

Get the alternate function for the specified pin (from 8 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

AFR@

( pin gpio-addr – af )

Get the alternate function for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

IDR@

( pin gpio-addr – input )

Get the input for the specified pin (from 0 to 15) on the specified GPIO.

RP2040 and RP2350 Words

gpio

CTRL_NORMAL

Normal control state for GPIO control

CTRL_INVERT

Inverse control state for GPIO control

CTRL_FORCE_LOW

Force low / disable control state for GPIO control

CTRL_FORCE_HIGH

Force high / enable control state for GPIO control

VOLTAGE_3.3V

Voltage set to 3.3V

VOLTAGE_1.8V

Voltage set to 1.8V

DRIVE_2MA

Drive strength set to 2mA

DRIVE_4MA

Drive strength set to 4mA

DRIVE_8MA

Drive strength set to 8mA

DRIVE_12MA

Drive strength set to 12mA

PAD_SWCLK

Pad index for SWCLK

PAD_SWD

Pad index for SWD

GPIO_IN

GPIO input register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OUT

GPIO output register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OUT_SET

GPIO output atomic bit-set register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OUT_CLR

GPIO output atomic bit-clear register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OUT_XOR

GPIO output atomic bit-xor register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OE

GPIO output enable register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OE_SET

GPIO output enable atomic bit-set register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OE_CLR

GPIO output enable atomic bit-clear register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_OE_XOR

GPIO output enable atomic bit-xor register; each bit corresponds to the GPIO with an index equal to its position

GPIO_STATUS_IRQTOPROC@

( index – flag )

Get interrupt to processors, after override is applied

GPIO_STATUS_IRQFROMPAD@

( index – flag )

Get interrupt from pad, before override is applied

GPIO_STATUS_INTOPERI@

( index – flag )

Get input signal to peripheral, after override is applied

GPIO_STATUS_INFROMPAD@

( index – flag )

Get input signal from pad, before override is applied

GPIO_STATUS_OETOPAD@

( index – flag )

Get output enable to pad, after register override is applied

\ applied

GPIO_STATUS_OEFROMPERI@

( index – flag )

Get output enable from selected peripheral, before register override is

GPIO_STATUS_OUTTOPAD@

( index – flag )

Get output signal to pad, after register override is applied

\ applied

GPIO_STATUS_OUTFROMPERI@

( index – flag )

Get output signal from selected peripheral, before register override is

GPIO_CTRL_IRQOVER!

( control index – )

Set interrupt state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_INOVER!

( control index – )

Set peripheral input state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_OEOVER!

( control index – )

Set output enable state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_OUTOVER!

( control index – )

Set output state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_FUNCSEL!

( function index – )

Set the function select for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_IRQOVER@

( index – control )

Get interrupt state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_INOVER@

( index – control )

Get peripheral input state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_OEOVER@

( index – control )

Get output enable state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_OUTOVER@

( index – control )

Get output state for GPIO

GPIO_CTRL_FUNCSEL@

( index – function )

Set the function select for GPIO

INTR_GPIO_EDGE_LOW!

( index – )

Clear a raw edge low interrupt

INTR_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH!

( index – )

Clear a raw edge high interrupt

INTR_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW@

( index – state )

Get a level low raw interrupt state

INTR_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH@

( index – state )

Get a level high raw interrupt state

INTR_GPIO_EDGE_LOW@

( index – state )

Get an edge low raw interrupt state

INTR_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH@

( index – state )

Get an edge high raw interrupt state

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW!

( enable index – )

Set a level low interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH!

( enable index – )

Set a level high interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_LOW!

( enable index – )

Set an edge low interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH!

( enable index – )

Set an edge high interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get a level low interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get a level high interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get an edge low interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get an edge high interrupt enable for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW!

( force index – )

Set a level low interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH!

( force index – )

Set a level high interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_LOW!

( force index – )

Set an edge low interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH!

( force index – )

Set an edge high interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW@

( index – force )

Get a level low interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH@

( index – force )

Get a level high interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_LOW@

( index – force )

Get an edge low interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH@

( index – force )

Get an edge high interrupt force for processor 0

PROC0_INTS_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get a level low interrupt status for processor 0

PROC0_INTS_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get a level high interrupt status for processor 0

PROC0_INTS_GPIO_EDGE_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get an edge low interrupt status for processor 0

PROC0_INTS_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get an edge high interrupt status for processor 0

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW!

( enable index – )

Set a level low interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH!

( enable index – )

Set a level high interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_LOW!

( enable index – )

Set an edge low interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH!

( enable index – )

Set an edge high interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get a level low interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get a level high interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get an edge low interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTE_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get an edge high interrupt enable for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW!

( force index – )

Set a level low interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH!

( force index – )

Set a level high interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_LOW!

( force index – )

Set an edge low interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH!

( force index – )

Set an edge high interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW@

( index – force )

Get a level low interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH@

( index – force )

Get a level high interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_LOW@

( index – force )

Get an edge low interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTF_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH@

( index – force )

Get an edge high interrupt force for processor 1

PROC1_INTS_GPIO_LEVEL_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get a level low interrupt status for processor 1

PROC1_INTS_GPIO_LEVEL_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get a level high interrupt status for processor 1

PROC1_INTS_GPIO_EDGE_LOW@

( index – enable )

Get an edge low interrupt status for processor 1

PROC1_INTS_GPIO_EDGE_HIGH@

( index – enable )

Get an edge high interrupt status for processor 1

PADS_BANK0_VOLTAGE_SELECT!

( voltage – )

Select voltage for pads

PADS_BANK0_VOLTAGE_SELECT@

( – voltage )

Get voltage for pads

PADS_BANK0_ISO!

( enable index – )

Set pad isolation control (rp2350 only)

PADS_BANK0_OD!

( disable index – )

Set output disable

PADS_BANK0_IE!

( enable index – )

Set input enable

PADS_BANK0_DRIVE!

( strength index – )

Set drive strength

PADS_BANK0_PUE!

( enable index – )

Set pull up enable

PADS_BANK0_PDE!

( enable index – )

Set pull down enable

PADS_BANK0_SCHMITT!

( enable index – )

Set schmitt trigger

PADS_BANK0_SLEWFAST!

( fast index – )

Set slew rate control

Heap Words

Heaps in zeptoforth are created by the user and consist of discretes blocks that are allocated, freed, and resized as multiples; the size of allocations plus a cell taken up by a block count is rounded up to the next full number of blocks. There is by default no global heap, and heaps created by the user are specifically not concurrency-safe; to make them concurrency-safe one must wrap them in locks, and because of the overhead this would impose, this is not done so by default. Note that the time taken up by heap allocation or resizing is bounded by a maximum which is defined by the number of blocks in the heap; any heap allocation or resizing may take this full time. On the other hand, the time taken up by freeing an allocation is determined solely by the number of blocks comprising the allocation.

heap

The following words are in heap:

heap-size

( block-size block-count – heap-bytes )

Get the size in bytes of a heap with the given block size in bytes and block count.

init-heap

( block-size block-count addr – )

Initialize a heap at addr with the given block size in bytes and block count; note that the size of the available memory at addr should be equal to or greater than the number of bytes returned by heap-size for block-size and block-count.

allocate

( size heap – addr )

Allocate memory in a heap of size bytes and return its address; if the memory cannot be allocated due to insufficient contiguous memory being available, x-allocate-failed is raised.

free

( addr heap – )

Free memory at addr in a heap.

resize

( size addr heap – new-addr )

Resize memory in a heap at addr to a new size in bytes, returning its new address. If sufficient memory is available for resizing at addr the allocation is expanded without moving or copying it and addr is returned. Otherwise, the allocation at addr is freed, and its contents is copied to a new allocation, whose address is returned. Note that if insufficient memory is available in the heap for resizing the allocation, the existing allocation is preserved, and x-allocate-failed is raised.

x-allocate-failed

( – )

This is an exception raised if allocation or resizing fails.

I2C Words

zeptoforth includes support for I2C peripherals on the RP2040 (e.g. the Raspberry Pi Pico) and the RP2350 (e.g.. the Raspberry Pi Pico 2). It supports both master and slave modes of operation on two different I2C peripheral devices, numbered 0 and 1. It supports clocks up to 1 MHz, as that is the limit supported by the RP2040’s I2C peripherals, and defaults to a clock of 400 kHz. Note that it does not currently support general calls or slaves sending NACK, and handling of interrupted sends when multiple masters are in use must be handled manually by the user.

i2c

The i2c module contains the following words:

enable-i2c

( i2c – )

Enable an I2C peripheral. Note that multiple nested enablings are permitted.

disable-i2c

( i2c – )

Disable an I2C peripheral. Note that multiple nested disablings are permitted.

i2c-clock!

( clock i2c – )

Set the clock for an I2C peripheral. Note that for most purposes a clock of 400000 is recommended, and it is this value to which the clock of an I2C peripheral defaults.

i2c-alternate

( i2c – alternate )

Get the alternate function for an I2C peripheral.

i2c-pin

( i2c pin – )

Configure a pin to be an I2C pin. In releases more recent than 1.14.1 this will set the pin to be an internal pull-up per the RP2040 and RP2350 datasheets/reference manuals. Previously it did not change the pull-up/pull-down configuration of the pin.

master-i2c

( i2c – )

Set an I2C peripheral to be a master.

slave-i2c

( i2c – )

Set an I2C peripheral to be a slave.

7-bit-i2c-addr

( i2c – )

Set an I2C peripheral to use 7-bit I2C addresses.

10-bit-i2c-addr

( i2c – )

Set an I2C peripheral to use 10-bit I2C addresses.

i2c-target-addr!

( i2c-addr i2c – )

Set the target address of an I2C peripheral.

i2c-slave-addr!

( i2c-addr i2c – )

Set the address of a slave I2C peripheral.

wait-i2c-master

( i2c – accepted )

Wait on a slave I2C peripheral for communication from an I2C master, and return either accept-send if the I2C master initiates sending data or accept-recv if the I2C master initiates receiving data. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if no communication is initiated before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

wait-i2c-master-send

( i2c – )

Wait on a slave I2C peripheral for the initiation of sending data from an I2C master. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if no send is initiated before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

wait-i2c-master-recv

( i2c – )

Wait on a slave I2C peripheral for the initiation of receiving data from an I2C master. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if no receive is initiated before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

>i2c

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Send data from a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes over an I2C peripheral. The number of bytes actually sent are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if sending is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

>i2c-stop

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Send data from a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes over an I2C peripheral and signal a STOP condition once sending is complete. The number of bytes actually sent are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if sending is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

>i2c-restart

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Send data from a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes over an I2C peripheral and signal a RESTART condition at the beginning of sending. The number of bytes actually sent are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if sending is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

>i2c-restart-stop

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Send data from a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes over an I2C peripheral, signaling a RESTART condition at the beginning of sending, and signal a STOP condition once sending is complete.The number of bytes actually sent are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if sending is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

i2c>

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Receive data into a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes from an I2C peripheral. The number of bytes actually received are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if receiving is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

i2c-stop>

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Receive data into a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes from an I2C peripheral and signal a STOP condition once receiving is complete. The number of bytes actually received are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if receiving is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

i2c-restart>

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Receive data into a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes from an I2C peripheral and signal a RESTART condition at the beginning of receiving. The number of bytes actually received are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if receiving is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

i2c-restart-stop>

( c-addr u i2c – u’ )

Receive data into a buffer defined by c-addr and u bytes from an I2C peripheral, signaling a RESTART condition at the beginning of receiving, and signal a STOP condition once receiving is complete. The number of bytes actually received are returned. If timeout (in the task module) is set to a value other than no-timeout a timeout in ticks (usually 100 µs per tick) is waited for, where if receiving is not complete before the timeout expires, x-timed-out is raised.

i2c-nack

( i2c – )

Set the next byte received by a slave I2C peripheral to be responded to with a NACK.

clear-i2c

( i2c – )

Reset the state of an I2C peripheral.

accept-send

( – constant )

Constant returned by wait-i2c-master on accepting a send from an I2C master.

accept-recv

( – constant )

Constant returned by wait-i2c-master on accepting a receive from an I2C master.

x-out-of-range-clock

( – )

Exception raised if an out of range clock is set with i2c-clock!.

x-i2c-target-noack

( – )

Exception raised if an I2C target address is not acknowledged.

x-arb-lost

( – )

Exception raised on arbitration lost.

x-i2c-tx-error

( – )

Exception raised on transmission error during sending.

x-i2c-rx-over

( – )

Exception raised on receive overflow; note that this should never happen, as this I2C driver configures the I2C peripherals to use clock stretching in case of RX FIFO full state.

x-invalid-i2c

( – )

Exception raised on specifying an invalid I2C peripheral index (i.e. one other than 0 or 1).

x-out-of-range-addr

( – )

Exception raised on specifying an invalid I2C address.

x-invalid-op-for-master-mode

( – )

Exception raised on a slave attempting to carry out an operation which is inappropriate for the state the master is in.

x-invalid-op-for-slave

( – )

Exception raised on a slave attempting to carry out an operation not permitted for slaves.

x-invalid-op-for-master

( – )

Exception raised on a master attempting to carry out an operation not permitted for masters.

x-master-not-ready

( – )

Exception for if a send or receive is attempted by a slave and the master is not in an appropriate state.

Interrupt Overloading Words

Interrupt overloading in an optional mechanism to enable multiple handlers to simultaneously share a single interrupt vector. It involves installing an adapter in the interrupt vector which calls the other handlers. Any preexisting interrupt handler is transferred to being the base handler of the adapter, which is always executed last out of all the handlers.

Both handlers and adapters can be uninstalled. Uninstalling a handler just disables that single handler while uninstalling the first adapter installed for a vector disables all handlers except for the base handler for that vector, which is reinstalled directly in the vector if present.

Note that if the user attempts to install more than one adapter on a single vector, only the first adapter is used, and all subsequent adapters are inactive. Inactive adapters have no effect on installing handlers, and uninstalling them is a no-op.

int-overload

The int-overload module contains the following words:

x-no-int-adapter

( – )

The no interrupt adapter available exception.

int-overload-size

( – bytes )

The size of an interrupt handler structure in bytes.

int-adapter-size

( – bytes )

The size of an interrupt adapter structure in bytes.

register-int-overload

( xt vector-index addr – )

Register an interrupt handler structure addr with an interrupt handler execution token xt for interrupt vector vector-index. If vector-index is out of range interrupt::x-invalid-vector is raised. If no interrupt adapter is installed for vector-index x-no-int-adapter is raised.

unregister-int-overload

( addr – )

Unregister an interrupt handler structure addr. After this point its associated interrupt handler will be removed.

register-int-adapter

( vector-index addr – )

Register an interrupt adapter structure addr for interrupt vector vector-index. If vector-index is out of range interrupt::x-invalid-vector is raised. If an interrupt adapter is already registered for vector-index then the interrupt adapter structure addr will be inactive.

unregister-int-adapter

( addr – )

Unregister an interrupt adapter structure addr. If there are interrupt handlers other than the base handler associated with this structure they are removed. A base handler associated with this structure is restored as the interrupt handler for the interrupt vector associated with this interrupt handler. Note that if this interrupt adapter is inactive this is a no-op.

Line Editor

The line editor provides a simple interface for allowing the user to edit input without the limitations in the normal refill mechanism. It provides both input history and a clipboard that is filled by deleting/cutting text. When enabled, the following keys can be used to control editing:

Backspace: delete/cut the character to the left of the cursor

Delete: delete/cut the character under the cursor

Left / Control-B: move the cursor one character to the left

Right / Control-F: move the cursor one character to the right

Up: switch to the previous line in the history

Down: switch to the next line in the history

Control-A: move the cursor to the start of the input

Control-E: move the cursor to the end of the input

Control-L: reset the terminal

Control-K: delete/cut to the end of the line from the cursor

Control-U: delete/cut to the start of the line from the cursor

Control-W: delete/cut to the start of the preceding word delimited by whitespace from the cursor

Control-Y: paste the current clipboard at the cursor

F1: enter upload mode, where line editing features are turned off

F2: leave upload mode and re-enable line editing features; this must be entered as the first key entered on a line

Note that tabs and characters of code points greater than 127 are handled correctly. Also note that it is not compatible with non-terminal operation except when in upload mode, i.e. with loading code automatically via serial or swdcom; before this is done one must be in upload mode or it must be disabled.

After a reboot, it is initialized for the main task only, and if, when enabled, refill is used for a different task, it needs to have already been initialized for that task.

line

The following words are in line:

init-line

( index-ptr count-ptr buffer-ptr buffer-size – )

Enable the line editor for the current task, with a pointer to the index variable, a poiner to the count variable, a pointer to the input buffer, and a size of the input buffer provided. Note that it allots memory in the current task’s dictionary.

forth

The following words are in forth:

enable-line

( – )

Enable the line editor.

disable-line

( – )

Disable the line editor. This must be done before loading code automatically.

Lock Words

A lock enforces mutual exclusion, typically with regard to control of a resource, between multiple tasks. It also serves as a queue for multiple tasks waiting on the lock which is held by another task. Furthermore, it provides a mechanism to avoid priority inversion, by temporarily elevating each task holding a lock’s priority to the maximum priority of all the tasks waiting for it; this applies even when chaining together multiple locks held by tasks holding some locks and waiting on others. Recursive lockings are permitted, with a recursive locking count being maintained by a given lock, which is finally released when all the lockings are matched by releases.

lock

The following words are in lock:

x-not-currently-owned

( – )

Exception raised if a task attempts to unlock a lock it is not the holder of.

lock-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of a lock in bytes.

init-lock

( addr – )

Initialize a lock starting at the specified address addr; note that it must be lock-size bytes in size.

claim-lock

( lock – )

Attempt to acquire a lock lock; if the lock is already held, put the current task in a queue and disable it. In that case, update the priority of the holder of a lock, and any subsequent holders of any locks waited for by the holder of this lock, in order to avoid priority inversion. Note that this must not be called within a critical section. Any number of lockings by the same task are permitted; the lock will be freed when they are balanced by an equal number of releasings.

release-lock

( lock – )

Attempt to release a lock lock if it is not recursively locked; if the current task is not the holder of the lock, raise x-not-currently-owned. If releasing the lock is successful, restore the priority of the current task to what it would be had its priority not been updated in order to avoid priority inversion; afterwards, carry out all the functionality that lock would carry out had it been called by the task at the head of the queue if there is one. If a lock lock is recursively locked, decrement the recursive lock count by one. Note that this must not be called within a critical section.

with-lock

( xt lock – )

Execute an xt with a given lock lock locked while it executes, unlocking it afterwards. If an exception is raised by xt, unlock lock and then re-raise the exception.

update-lock-priority

( lock – )

Update the priority of the holder of a lock, and the priority of the holder of a lock waited on by the holder of this lock, and so on, in order to avoid priority inversion. Note that this must not be called within a critical section.

Map Words

Maps in zeptoforth are implemented as fixed-sized hash tables. They have fixed-sized keys and values; it is recommended that these be either addresses or indices into some other data structure, for sake of economy of space. For the sake of alignment, the amount of space taken up by a key and a value together is internally rounded up to the nearest cell.

map

The following words are in map:

map-size

( count key-size value-size – map-bytes )

Get the size in bytes of a map with an entry count count, a key size key-size in bytes, and a value size value-size in bytes.

init-map

( hash-xt equals-xt remove-xt count key-size value-size addr – )

Initialize a map at addr with a key size key-size in bytes, a value size value-size in bytes, an entry count count, an entry removal handler remove-xt with the signature ( value-addr key-addr – ) which can be 0, an equals function equals-xt with the signature ( key-addr key-addr – equals? ), and a hash function hash-xt with the signature ( key-addr – hash ).

find-map

( key-addr map – value-addr | 0 )

Find a the value of a key at key-addr in a map map and return the address of its value value-addr, or if the key is not found, return 0.

insert-map

( value-addr key-addr map – )

Insert a value at value-addr at the key at key-addr in a map map. If the key is already present in the map, call the entry removal handler for the key and value already in the map (if set) and then replace the key and value in the map with those provided. If the key is not already present in the map and there is room for another entry in the map, add the value to the map at the specified key, otherwise raise x-map-full.

remove-map

( key-addr map – )

Remove a value with a key at key-addr from a map map if it is present; if this is the case, first call the entry removal handler for the key and value already in the map (if set).

first-map

( map – index | -1 )

Get the index index of the first entry in a map map or return -1 if the map is empty.

next-map

( index map – index’ | -1 )

Get the next index index’ of an entry in a map map after the entry at the index index; if there is no following entry, return -1.

at-map

( index map – value-addr key-addr )

Get the value and key at value-addr and key-addr of the entry in map map at index index; if index is out of range, raise x-map-index-out-of-range, and if index does not correspond to a valid entry, raise x-map-index-no-entry.

clear-map

( map – )

Clear map map of all entries, calling the entry removal handler for each cleared entry if set.

copy-map

( src-map dest-map – )

Copy each entry in the source map src-map into the destination map dest-map, overwriting existing entries with identical keys (and calling the entry removal handler for them, if set for the destination map). If insufficient room is available to copy further entries into the destination map, x-map-full is raised. If the key size, value size, hash function, or equals function differ between the two maps, x-dest-map-not-match is raised.

map-entry-count

( map – entry-count )

Get the total entry count of a map map.

map-used-entry-count

( map – used-entry-count )

Get the used entry count of a map map.

map-key-size

( map – key-size )

Get the key size in bytes of a map map.

map-value-size

( map – value-size )

Get the value size in bytes of a map map.

map-hash-xt

( map – hash-xt )

Get the hash function of a map map.

map-equals-xt

( map – equals-xt )

Get the equals function of a map map.

map-remove-xt )

( map – remove-xt )

Get the entry removal handler of a map map.

x-map-full

( – )

Map is full exception.

x-map-index-out-of-range

( – )

Map index is out of range exception.

x-map-index-no-entry

( – )

Map index has no entry exception.

x-dest-map-not-match

( – )

Destination map does not match source map with regard to key size, value size, hash function, or equals function exception.

Counted String Maps

Counted string maps are a subset of maps that have keys that are implemented as counted strings allocated (aside from an address) outside of the map data structure.

cstr-map

The following words are in cstr-map:

cstr-map-size

( count value-size – map-bytes )

Get the size in bytes of a counted string map with an entry count count and a value size value-size in bytes.

init-cstr-map

( hash-xt equals-xt remove-xt count key-size value-size addr – )

Initialize a counted string map at addr with a value size value-size in bytes, an entry count count, and an entry removal handler remove-xt with the signature ( value-addr key-addr – ) which can be 0.

find-cstr-map

( key-cstr cstr-map – value-addr | 0 )

Find a the value of a counted string key key-cstr in a counted string map cstr-map and return the address of its value value-addr, or if the key is not found, return 0.

insert-cstr-map

( value-addr key-cstr cstr-map – )

Insert a value at value-addr at the counted string key key-cstr in a counted string map cstr-map. If the key is already present in the map, call the entry removal handler for the key and value already in the map (if set) and then replace the key and value in the map with those provided. If the key is not already present in the map and there is room for another entry in the map, add the value to the map at the specified key, otherwise raise x-map-full.

remove-cstr-map

( key-cstr cstr-map – )

Remove a value with a counted string key key-cstr from a counted string map cstr-map if it is present; if this is the case, first call the entry removal handler for the key and value already in the map (if set).

at-cstr-map

( index cstr-map – value-addr key-cstr )

Get the value at value-addr and counted string key key-cstr of the entry in a counted string map cstr-map at index index; if index is out of range, raise x-map-index-out-of-range, and if index does not correspond to a valid entry, raise x-map-index-no-entry.

Integer Maps

Integer maps are a subset of maps that have keys that are cell-sized integers.

int-map

The following words are in int-map:

int-map-size

( count value-size – map-bytes )

Get the size in bytes of a integer map with an entry count count and a value size value-size in bytes.

init-int-map

( hash-xt equals-xt remove-xt count key-size value-size addr – )

Initialize a integer map at addr with a value size value-size in bytes, an entry count count, and an entry removal handler remove-xt with the signature ( value-addr key-addr – ) which can be 0.

find-int-map

( key-int int-map – value-addr | 0 )

Find a the value of a integer key key-int in a map int-map and return the address of its value value-addr, or if the key is not found, return 0.

insert-int-map

( value-addr key-int int-map – )

Insert a value at value-addr at the integer key key-int in an integer map int-map. If the key is already present in the map, call the entry removal handler for the key and value already in the map (if set) and then replace the key and value in the map with those provided. If the key is not already present in the map and there is room for another entry in the map, add the value to the map at the specified key, otherwise raise x-map-full.

remove-int-map

( key-int int-map – )

Remove a value with a integer key key-int from an integer map int-map if it is present; if this is the case, first call the entry removal handler for the key and value already in the map (if set).

at-int-map

( index int-map – value-addr key-int )

Get the value at value-addr and integer key key-int of the entry in an integer map int-map at index index; if index is out of range, raise x-map-index-out-of-range, and if index does not correspond to a valid entry, raise x-map-index-no-entry.

Module Words

Modules in zeptoforth are built on top of wordlists, and form a user-friendly means of controlling word namespaces instead of manually manipulating wordlists. Modules and wordlists are one and the same, but by convention they are named with *.

At any given time once src/forth/common/module.fs is loaded there is a module stack which controls how module words manipulate the wordlist order. Initially there is one entry on the module stack, corresponding to the forth wordlist. When new entries are pushed onto the module stack, they save the state of base prior to their creation, and restore it once they are popped. Also, module stack entries specify the current wordlist for them, and when module stack entries immediately above them on the stack are popped, their wordlist is restored as the current wordlist.

A new module is defined by begin-module; the module named must not exist yet. An existing module can be extended by continue-module; the named module must exist. Definitions after that point are added to the module, until end-module or end-module> is seen.

Within a given module, the user may import and unimport modules/wordlists, which pushes them on the wordlist order and removes them from that module’s portion of the wordlist’s order respectively. Note that all the wordlists imported with a module definition are automatically unimported when that module definition is ended.

Words inside modules or inside nested modules may be used without importing the modules in question with paths specified with module::word or, mor generally, module0::…::modulen::word. These paths can be used not simply by the outer interpreter but also by any word which looks up another word by name, such as ', ['], postpone, averts, and triggers.

Note that it is recommended that once src/common/forth/module.fs is loaded, the user should not manually use set-order or set-current, as the module system will not know about this and thus unexpected results may occur.

forth

The following words are defined in forth:

x-already-defined

( – )

Module already defined exception.

x-not-found

( – )

Module not found exception.

begin-module

( “name” – )

Begin the definition of module name; module name must not already exist or x-already-defined will be raised.

continue-module

( “name” – )

Continue the definition of a preexisting module name; if module name does not exist x-not-found will be raised.

private-module

( – )

Begin the definition of a private module, i.e a module not bound to a word.

end-module

( – )

End the definition of the module at the top of the module stack, removing each wordlist for each module imported within it from the wordlist order.

end-module>

( – module )

End the definition of the module at the top of the module stack, removing each wordlist for each module imported within it from th e wordlist order, and then push the module whose definition had ended onto the data stack.

import

( module – )

Import a specified module into the current module’s wordlist order; if the module does not exist x-not-found is raised.

import-from

( module “name” – )

Import a specified named word from within the specified module into the current namespace; note that this word will not shadow identically named words defined in the current namespace, and will persist until the end of the current module’s definition.

begin-imports-from

( module “name0” … “namen” “end-imports-from” – )

Import multiple specified named words from within the specified module into the current namespace; note that these words will not shadow identically named words defined in the current namespace, and will persist untilt he end of the current module’s definition. Note that these imports can cross multiple lines of input, as in:

begin-module foobar
  : foo ." FOO " ;
  : bar ." BAR " ;
  : baz ." BAZ " ;
end-module

foobar begin-imports-from
  foo bar
end-imports-from

unimport

( module – )

Remove a specified module from the current module’s wordlist order; note that it does not remove it from parent modules’ wordlist orders, so if it had been imported within them they are still searchable.

export

( xt “word-name” – )

Export xt from the module currently being defined as word-name.

Programmable Input/Output Words

Programmable input/output (PIO) on the RP2040 (i.e. the Raspberry Pi Pico) and the RP2350 (i.e. the Raspberry Pi Pico 2) provides a means to input to or output from pins in a very high-speed fashion at some speed up to the system clock of 125 MHz, on the RP2040, or 150 MHz, on the RP2350. There are two PIO peripherals, PIO0 and PIO1, on the RP2040, and a third PIO peripheral, PIO2, on the RP2350, each of which contain four state machines.

PIO’s may have up to 32 PIO instructions in their memory, which are 16 bits in size each. PIO state machines may be set to wrap from a top instruction to a bottom instruction automatically, unless a jmp instruction is executed at the top address. Instructions may be loaded into a PIO’s instruction memory with pio-instr-mem! or pio-instr-relocate-mem!. Instructions may also be fed into a state machine to be executed immediately with sm-instr!. The address to execute PIO instructions at may be set for a state machine with sm-addr!

Up to four PIO state machines may be enabled, disabled, or reset at a time with sm-enable, sm-disable, or sm-restart respectively. These take a bitset of four bits where the position of each bit corresponds to the index of the state machine to enable, disable, or restart.

Each PIO state machine has four 32-bit registers, an input shift register (ISR), an output shift register (OSR), an X register, and a Y register. They also have a 5-bit program counter (PC). These are all initialized to zero.

Each PIO state machine has an RX FIFO and a TX FIFO of four 32-bit values each. These are initialized to empty. Note that the RX FIFO and TX FIFO on a PIO state machine may be joined into a single unidirectional FIFO consisting of eight 32-bit values. The RX FIFO for a state machine may be pushed to from a state machine’s ISR register, which is 32-bits in size. The TX FIFO for a state machine may be pulled from to a state machine’s OSR register, which is also 32-bits in size.

PIO state machines may automatically pull from its TX FIFO after a threshold number of bits have been shifted out of its OSR register. They may also automatically push to its RX FIFO after a threshold number of bits have been shifted into its ISR register.

The clock divider for a state machine is set with sm-clkdiv!, which takes a fractional component (from 0 to 255) and an integral component (from 0 to 65536) to divide the system clock by for the clock rate of the state machine in question. Note that if the integral clock divisor is 0 it is treated as 65536, and in those cases the fractional clock divisor must be 0.

PIO state machines may have an optional delay in cycles associated with each PIO instruction and may have sideset enabled for up to five pins; the sideset pins belong to the upper bits in the delay/sideset fields for instructions that have them and the delay pins belong to the lower bits in said fields. Sideset pin bits set the state of pins each cycle simultaneous with whatever other operations they are carrying out. sm-sideset-pins! sets the number of bits that will be used for sideset. Note that the highest bit in the five-bit delay/sideset field may be optionally set to mean sideset enabled if sm-sideset-high-enable! is set, leaving four bits for delay and sideset.

The legacy way of defining a PIO program is simply to use create to give it a name, then lists the instructions one at a time. This requires manually dealing with addresses in jumps, as well as program attributes such as the wrap points.

A more convenient way to define a PIO program is using the :pio defining word. Following that, the instructions are given including some additional ones that work only in the context of a :pio and are defined in word list pioasm. Such a PIO program is ended with ;pio. Space for a program can be allocated by alloc-piomem. It can then be loaded and set up with setup-prog, which takes care of loading as well as setting transfer address and wrap in a single operation. Similar to the armv6m module, in this mode jumps use “marks”, which are cells on the data stack, for forward and backward references.

PIO assembler words compile PIO instructions to here as 16 bits per instruction. There are two different basic types of PIO instructions - instructions without an associated delay or sideset, and instructions with an associated delay and/or sideset. The latter kind of instruction is marked with an + in its assembling word.

pio

The pio module contains the following words:

Constants

on

( – state )

On state.

off

( – state )

Off state.

right

( – direction )

Right direction.

left

( – direction )

Left direction.

PIO0

( – pio )

PIO0.

PIO1

( – pio )

PIO1.

PIO2

( – pio )

PIO2 (`rp2350 only).

IRQ0

( – irq )

IRQ0 index.

IRQ1

( – irq )

IRQ1 index.

PIO0_IRQ0

( – irq )

PIO0 IRQ0 index.

PIO0_IRQ1

( – irq )

PIO0 IRQ1 index.

PIO1_IRQ0

( – irq )

PIO1 IRQ0 index.

PIO1_IRQ1

( – irq )

PIO1 IRQ1 index.

PIO2_IRQ0

( – irq )

PIO2 IRQ0 index (rp2350 only).

PIO2_IRQ1

( – irq )

PIO2 IRQ1 index (rp2350 only).

PIO Words

pins-pio-alternate

( pin-base pin-count pio – )

Configure GPIO pins starting from pin-base of a count up to pin-count to be in an alternate function state such that the PIO may make use to them. Note that the pins wrap around, e.g. 29 3 PIO0 pins-pio-alternate configures GPIO pins 29, 0, and 1.

Note: this was previously specified as not being needed with sm-sideset-pins!, sm-set-pins!, or sm-out-pins!, but as it turned out that this could not be implemented as intended with sm-sideset-pins!, this functionality was removed from sm-sideset-pins!, and for the sake of consistency, from sm-set-pins! and sm-out-pins! as well. Conversely, this is not needed for inputs, as the PIO does not require alternate functions to input from GPIO pins.

pio-instr-mem!

( addr count pio – )

Write count halfwords starting at addr to instruction memory starting at instruction 0.

pio-instr-relocate-mem!

( addr count offset pio – )

Write count halfwords starting at addr to instruction memory starting at instruction offset, relocating any JMP instructions in the process so that a destination of 0 is relocated to offset and so on.

pio-interrupt-enable

( interrupt-bits irq pio – )

Enable interrupts.

pio-interrupt-disable

( interrupt-bits irq pio – )

Disable interrupts.

pio-interrupt-enable-force

( interrupt-bits irq pio – )

Enable forcing interrupts.

pio-interrupt-disable-force

( interrupt-bits irq pio – )

Disable forcing interrupts.

pio-interrupt-raw@

( pio – interrupt-bits )

Get raw interrupts.

pio-interrupt@

( irq pio – interrupt-bits )

Get interrupt status.

INT_SM

( state-machine – index )

Interrupt bits.

INT_SM_TXNFULL

( state-machine – index )

TXN not full interupt bits.

INT_SM_RXNEMPTY

( state-machine – index )

RXN not empty interrupt bits.

State Machine Words

sm-enable

( state-machine-bits pio – )

Enable state machines.

sm-disable

( state-machine-bits pio – )

Disable state machines.

sm-restart

( state-machine-bits pio – )

Restart state machines.

sm-clkdiv!

( fractional integral state-machine pio – )

Set the clock divisor for a state machine.

sm-addr!

( address state-machine pio – )

Set the address for a state machine.

sm-wrap!

( bottom-address top-address state-machine pio – )

Set the wrapping of a state machine.

sm-out-sticky!

( sticky state-machine pio – )

Set the sticky state of a state machine.

sm-sideset-high-enable!

( on/off state-machine pio – )

Enable using the highest bit in the delay/sideset fields of instructions as a sideset enable bit for a state machine. This leaves four bits in the delay/sideset fields of instructions for delay and sideset.

sm-sideset-pindir!

( on/off state-machine pio – )

Set sideset data assserted to pin directions pit.

sm-jmp-pin!

( pin state-machine pio – )

Set GPIO number to use as condition for JMP PIN.

sm-inline-out-enable!

( pin state-machine pio – )

Set a bit of OUT data to use as an inline OUT enable.

sm-inline-out-enable-clear

( state-machine pio – )

Disable using a bit of OUT data as an inline OUT enable.

sm-pull-threshold!

( threshold state-machine pio – )

Set OSR threshold before autopull or conditional pull will take place; value may be from 1 to 32.

sm-push-threshold!

( threshold state-machine pio – )

Set ISR threshold before autopush or conditional push will take place; value may be from 1 to 32.

sm-in-count!

( in-count state-machine pio – )

Set number of pins which are not masked to 0 when read by an IN PINS, WAIT PIN, or MOV x, PINS instruction; value may be from 1 to 32 (rp2350 only).

sm-txf!

( x state-machine pio – )

Write to the TX FIFO of a state machine.

sm-rxf@

( state-machine pio – x )

Read from the RX FIFO of a state machine.

sm-pin!

( on/off pin state-machine pio – )

Set the on/off state of a pin for a state machine. Note that the state machine should be disabled.

sm-pindir!

( out/in pin state-machine pio – )

State the out/in state of a pin for a state machine. Note that the state machine should be disabled.

sm-sideset-pins!

( pin-base pin-count state-machine pio – )

Set the sideset pins for a state machine. Note that the state machine should be disabled.

sm-set-pins!

( pin-base pin-count state-machine pio – )

Set the SET pins for a state machine. Note that the state machine should be disabled.

sm-out-pins!

( pin-base pin-count state-machine pio – )

Set the OUT pins for a state machine. Note that the state machine should be disabled.

sm-in-pin-base!

( pin-base state-machine pio – )

Set the IN pin base for a state machine. Note that the state machine should be disabled.

sm-rx-fifo-level@

( state-machine pio – level )

Get a state machine RX FIFO level.

sm-tx-fifo-level@

( state-machine pio – level )

Get a state machine TX FIFO level.

sm-join-rx-fifo!

( join? state-machine pio – )

Set joining the RX FIFO and TX FIFO of a state machine into a single eight by 32-bit RX FIFO.

sm-join-tx-fifo!

( join? state-machine pio – )

Set joining the RX FIFO and TX FIFO of a state machine into a single eight by 32-bit TX FIFO.

sm-out-shift-dir

( direction state-machine pio – )

Set the output shift register direction.

sm-in-shift-dir

( direction state-machine pio – )

Set the input shift register direction.

sm-autopull!

( on/off state-machine pio – )

Set autopull on/off.

sm-autopush!

( on/off state-machine pio – )

Set autopush on/off.

sm-instr!

( addr count state-machine pio – )

Manually write instructions to a state machine.

Words for “new style” PIO programs

:pio

( “name” – pio-mark )

Starts the definition of PIO program name. This imports word list pioasm to enable words that are only valid within a PIO program. End the definition with ;pio.

;pio

( pio-mark – )

Ends the definition of the PIO program begun with :pio.

p-code

( prog – code )

The start of the code (PIO instructions) for the given PIO program.

p-size

( prog – size )

Program size in instructions for the given PIO program.

p-wrap-bot

( prog – wrap-bot )

Wrap bottom for the given PIO program.

p-wrap-top

( prog – wrap-top )

Wrap top for the given PIO program.

p-wrap

( prog – wrap-bot wrap-top )

Both wrap points for the given PIO program.

p-transfer

( prog – transfer )

Transfer (start) address for the given PIO program.

p-prog

( prog – code size )

Code address and program length for the given PIO program, suitable for pio-instr-mem!.

alloc-piomem

( pio size – base )

Allocate space for a program of length size in the specified PIO (PIO0 or PIO1) and returns the base address. Raises x-pio-no-room if there is no room for a program of that size in the specified PIO.

free-piomem

( pio base size – )

Frees previously allocated PIO program space.

setup-prog

( state-machine pio prog base – )

This loads the specified program (defined by :pio) into pio starting at base and sets up state-machine in that PIO to run it. The starting address and wrap parameters are set from the program attributes, i.e., sm-wrap! and sm-addr! have been done. Other state machine specific setup such as pin mappings, as well as FIFO and clock parameters, have to be done separately.

In some applications the same program is used in several state machines of the same PIO, which allows the same program words to drive both state machines. The simplest way to deal with this is to invoke setup-prog once for each state machine, with the same base each time. That will load the program words each time, but this is harmless.

PIO Assembler Words

jmp,

( address condition – )

PIO JMP instruction. Branch, conditionally or unconditionally. Condition is the condition, with or without a decrement, to apply to whether to branch. Address is the PIO instruction address to branch to.

wait,

( index source polarity – )

PIO WAIT instruction. Wait for a condition to be true. Polarity is whether to wait for a 1 or a 0. Source is whether to wait for an absolute GPIO pin, a pin relative to the absolute IN pin base, or a PIO IRQ index. Index is the pin or PIO IRQ index to wait for.

in,

( bit-count source – )

PIO IN instruction. Input bits from a source into the current state machine’s ISR register. Source is the source to shift bits into the ISR register for the current state machine into, according to the configured shift in direction. Bit-count is how many bits to shift, a value from 1 to 32. The ISR bit shift count is increased by the bit count, saturating at 32.

out,

( bit-count destination – )

PIO OUT instruction. Output bits from the current state machine’s OSR register to a destination. Destination is the destination to shift bits into from the OSR register for the current state machine, according to the configured shift out direction. Bit-count is how many bits to shift, value from 1 to 32. The OSR bit shift count is increased by the bit count, saturating at 32.

push,

( block if-full – )

PIO PUSH instruction. Push the contents of the current state machine’s ISR register into the current state machine’s RX FIFO and reset the ISR register to all zeros. If-full is the condition as to whether to conditionally push. Block is whether to stall if pushing is not possible due to the RX FIFO being full.

pull,

( block if-empty – )

PIO PULL instruction. Pull a 32-bit value from the current state machine’s TX FIFO into the current state machine’s OSR register. If-empty is the condition as to whether to conditionally pull. Block is whether to stall if pulling is not possible due to the TX FIFO being empty.

mov,

( source op destination – )

PIO MOV instruction. Transfer a value from source to destination, applying op (which may be a no-op) to the value in the process.

mov-isr-rx-idx-imm,

( index – )

PIO MOV ISR to RX instruction, with an immediate index. Transfer a value from the ISR to an immediate index in the RX FIFO.

mov-isr-rx-idx-y,

( – )

PIO MOV ISR to RX instruction, indexed by the Y register. Transfer a value from the ISR to an index in the RX FIFO determined by the Y register.

mov-rx-osr-idx-imm,

( index – )

PIO MOV RX to OSR instruction, with an immediate index. Transfer a value from an immediate index in the RX FIFO to the OSR.

mov-rx-osr-idx-y,

( – )

PIO MOV RX to OSR instruction, indexed by the Y register. Transfer a value from an index in the RX FIFO determined by the Y register to the OSR.

irq,

( index set/wait – )

PIO IRQ instruction. Set or wait on a PIO IRQ index, from 0 to 7 before REL is applied. Note that REL can be used to mark a PIO IRQ as relative to the current state machine ID by adding the state machine ID to the lower two bits of the IRQ index, by way of module-4 addition on the two LSB’s.

set,

( data destination – )

PIO SET instruction. Set destination to data, which is a value from $00 to $1F.

jmp+,

( address delay/side-set condition – )

PIO JMP instruction with delay or side-set. Branch, conditionally or unconditionally. Condition is the condition, with or without a decrement, to apply to whether to branch. Address is the PIO instruction address to branch to. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

wait+,

( index delay/side-set source polarity – )

PIO WAIT instruction with delay or side-set. Wait for a condition to be true. Polarity is whether to wait for a 1 or a 0. Source is whether to wait for an absolute GPIO pin, a pin relative to the absolute IN pin base, or a PIO IRQ index. Index is the pin or PIO IRQ index to wait for. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

in+,

( bit-count delay/side-set source – )

PIO IN instruction with delay or side-set. Input bits from a source into the current state machine’s ISR register. Source is the source to shift bits into the ISR register for the current state machine into, according to the configured shift in direction. Bit-count is how many bits to shift, a value from 1 to 32. The ISR bit shift count is increased by the bit count, saturating at 32. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

out+,

( bit-count delay/side-set destination – )

PIO OUT instruction with delay or side-set. Output bits from the current state machine’s OSR register to a destination. Destination is the destination to shift bits into from the OSR register for the current state machine, according to the configured shift out direction. Bit-count is how many bits to shift, value from 1 to 32. The OSR bit shift count is increased by the bit count, saturating at 32. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

push+,

( delay/side-set block if-full – )

PIO PUSH instruction with delay or side-set. Push the contents of the current state machine’s ISR register into the current state machine’s RX FIFO and reset the ISR register to all zeros. If-full is the condition as to whether to conditionally push. Block is whether to stall if pushing is not possible due to the RX FIFO being full. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

pull+,

( delay/side-set block if-empty – )

PIO PULL instruction with delay or side-set. Pull a 32-bit value from the current state machine’s TX FIFO into the current state machine’s OSR register. If-empty is the condition as to whether to conditionally pull. Block is whether to stall if pulling is not possible due to the TX FIFO being empty.

mov+,

( source delay/side-set op destination – )

PIO MOV instruction with delay or side-set. Transfer a value from source to destination, applying op (which may be a no-op) to the value in the process. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

mov-isr-rx-idx-imm+,

( delay/side-set index – )

PIO MOV ISR to RX instruction, with an immediate index, with delay or side-set. Transfer a value from the ISR to an immediate index in the RX FIFO.

mov-isr-rx-idx-y+,

( delay/side-set – )

PIO MOV ISR to RX instruction, indexed by the Y register, with delay or side-set. Transfer a value from the ISR to an index in the RX FIFO determined by the Y register.

mov-rx-osr-idx-imm+,

( delay/side-set index – )

PIO MOV RX to OSR instruction, with an immediate index, with delay or side-set. Transfer a value from an immediate index in the RX FIFO to the OSR.

mov-rx-osr-idx-y+,

( delay/side-set – )

PIO MOV RX to OSR instruction, indexed by the Y register, with delay or side-set. Transfer a value from an index in the RX FIFO determined by the Y register to the OSR.

irq+,

( index delay/side-set set/wait – )

PIO IRQ instruction with delay or side-set. Set or wait on a PIO IRQ index, from 0 to 7 before REL is applied. Note that REL can be used to mark a PIO IRQ as relative to the current state machine ID by adding the state machine ID to the lower two bits of the IRQ index, by way of module-4 addition on the two LSB’s. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

set+,

( data delay/side-set destination – )

PIO SET instruction with delay or side-set. Set destination to data, which is a value from $00 to $1F. Delay/side-set is either a number of state machine cycles to delay after the instruction is executed, or up to five bits to write to the pins configured to sideset, depending upon how the current state machine is configured.

Module pioasm

These words are useful only within the context of a :pio program definition. They are in the pioasm word list, which is automatically imported by :pio and unimported by ;pio.

mark<

( – jmp-mark )

Mark a backward destination.

>mark

( jmp-mark – )

Mark a forward destination.

jmp>

( condition – jmp-mark )

Forward PIO JMP to next unmatched >mark, without delay/side-set.

jmp<

( jmp-mark condition – )

Backward jump to preceding unmatched mark<, without delay or side-set.

jmp+>

( delay/side-set condition – mark-add marker )

Forward PIO JMP to next unmatched >mark with delay or side-set.

jmp+<

( jmp-mark marker delay/side-set condition – )

Backward jump to preceding unmatched mark< with delay or side-set.

wrap<

( – )

Set wrap bottom at this line (defaults to first instruction).

<wrap

( – )

Set wrap top at preceding line (defaults to end of program).

start>

( – )

Set transfer address (program start) at this line (defaults to first instruction).

COND_ALWAYS

( – condition )

Always jump.

COND_X0=

( – condition )

Jump if scratch X is zero.

COND_X1-

( – condition )

Jump if scratch X is non-zero, post-decrement.

COND_Y0=

( – condition )

Jump if scratch Y is zero.

COND_Y1-

( – condition )

Jump if scratch Y is non-zero, post-decrement.

COND_XY<>

( – condition )

Jump if scratch X not equal scratch Y.

COND_PIN

( – condition )

Jump on input pin.

COND_IOSRE

( – condition )

Jump on output shift register not empty.

WAIT_GPIO

( – wait )

Wait for GPIO.

WAIT_PIN

( – wait )

Wait for a pin.

WAIT_IRQ

( – wait )

Wait for an IRQ.

WAIT_JMPPIN

( – wait )

Wait on the pin indexed by the PINCTRL_JMP_PIN configuration, plus an index in the range 0-3, modulo 32 (rp2350 only).

IN_PINS

( – in-source )

Pins input.

IN_X

( – in-source )

Scratch register X input.

IN_Y

( – in-source )

Scratch register Y input.

IN_NULL

( – in-source )

NULL input (all zeros).

IN_ISR

( – in-source )

ISR input.

IN_OSR

( – in-source )

OSR input.

OUT_PINS

( – out-destination )

Pins output.

OUT_X

( – out-destination )

Scratch register X output.

OUT_Y

( – out-destination )

Scratch register Y output.

OUT_NULL

( – out-destination )

NULL output (discard data).

OUT_PINDIRS

( – out-destination )

PINDIRs output.

OUT_PC

( – out )

PC output (unconditional jump to shifted address).

OUT_ISR

( – out )

ISR output (also sets ISR shift counter to bit count).

OUT_EXEC

( – out )

Execute OSR shift data as instruction.

PUSH_NOT_FULL

( – push-if-full-option )

Push data even if threshold is not met.

PUSH_IF_FULL

( – push-if-full-option )

Do nothing unless the total input shift count has reached its threshold.

PUSH_NO_BLOCK

( – push-block-option )

Do not stall execution if RX FIFO is full, instead drop data from ISR.

PUSH_BLOCK

( – push-block-option )

Stall execution if RX FIFO is full.

PULL_NOT_EMPTY

( – pull-if-full-option )

Pull data even if threshold is not met.

PULL_IF_EMPTY

( – pull-if-full-option )

Do nothing unless the total output shift count has reached its threshold.

PULL_NO_BLOCK

( – pull-block-option )

Do not stall execution if TX FIFO is empty, instead copy from scratch X.

PULL_BLOCK

( – pull-block-option )

Stall execution if TX FIFO is empty.

MOV_DEST_PINS

( – mov-destination )

Move to PINS.

MOV_DEST_X

( – mov-destination )

Move to scratch register X.

MOV_DEST_Y

( – mov-destination )

Move to scratch register Y.

MOV_DEST_PINDIRS

( – mov-destination )

Move to PINDIRS (rp2350 only).

MOV_DEST_EXEC

( – mov-destination )

Move to EXEC (execute data as instruction).

MOV_DEST_PC

( – mov-destination )

Move to PC (treat data as address for unconditional branch).

MOV_DEST_ISR

( – mov-destination )

Move to ISR (input shift counter is reset to 0, i.e. empty).

MOV_DEST_OSR

( – mov-destination )

Move to OSR (output shift counter is reset to 0, i.e. full).

MOV_OP_NONE

( – mov-op )

Move operation none.

MOV_OP_INVERT

( – mov-op )

Move operation invert.

MOV_OP_REVERSE

( – mov-op )

Move operation bit-reverse.

MOV_SRC_PINS

( – mov-op )

Move from PINS.

MOV_SRC_X

( – mov-source )

Move from scratch register X.

MOV_SRC_Y

( – mov-source )

Move from scratch register Y.

MOV_SRC_NULL

( – mov-source )

Move from NULL.

MOV_SRC_STATUS

( – mov-source )

Move from STATUS.

MOV_SRC_ISR

( – mov-source )

Move from ISR.

MOV_SRC_OSR

( – mov-source )

Move from OSR.

IRQ_SET

( – irq-op )

Raise an IRQ.

IRQ_CLEAR

( – irq-op )

Clear an IRQ.

IRQ_WAIT

( – irq-op )

Wait for an IRQ to be lowered.

SET_PINS

( – set-destination )

Set PINS.

SET_X

( – set-destination )

Set scratch register X (5 LSBs are set to data, all others are cleared).

SET_Y

( – set-destination )

Set scratch register Y (5 LSBs are set to data, all others are cleared).

SET_PINDIRS

( – set-destination )

Set PINDIRS.

PREV

( irq – irq-prev )

Reference an IRQ in the previous-numbered PIO, wrapping around (rp2350 only).

REL

( irq – irq-rel )

Add the state machine ID to the lower two bits of the IRQ index, by way of module-4 addition on the two LSB’s.

NEXT

( irq – irq-next )

Reference an IRQ in the next-numbered PIO, wrapping around (rp2350 only).

Exceptions

x-sm-out-of-range

( – )

State machine out of range exception.

x-pio-out-of-range

( – )

PIO out of range exception.

x-too-many-instructions

( – )

Too many instructions exception.

x-address-out-of-range

( – )

Address out of range exception.

x-too-many-pins

( – )

Too many pins exception.

x-pin-out-of-range

( – )

Pin out of range exception.

x-clkdiv-out-of-range

( – )

Clock divisor out of range exception.

x-irq-out-of-range

( – )

IRQ out of range exception.

x-interrupt-out-of-range

( – )

Interrupt out of range exception.

x-threshold-out-of-range

( – )

Buffer threshold out of range exception.

x-bit-out-of-range

( – )

Bit out of range exception.

x-relocate-out-of-range

( – )

Relocation out of range exception.

x-in-pio

( – )

:pio when inside a previous :pio exception.

x-not-in-pio

( – )

;pio or other word valid only after :pio exception.

x-incorrect-mark-type

( – )

Wrong mark for jump or mark exception.

x-pio-no-room

( – )

alloc-piomem has no room for a program this big exception.

x-invalid-size

( – )

alloc-piomem size argument > 32 exception.

x-invalid-base

( – )

Invalid program base address in setup-prog or free-piomem exception.

x-invalid-gpio-base

( – )

Invalid GPIO base (i.e. not 0 or 16) exception (rp2350 only).

PIO/state machine pools

From release 1.16.0 on there is a PIO/state machine pool mechanism that provides a centralized means of allocating PIO blocks and state machines integrated with PIO memory management.

Multiple state machines on a single PIO block can be allocated at once with this mechanism. This is useful in cases where one needs multiple state machines to communicate with one another via IRQ’s and thus limitations are imposed on which PIO’s the state machines are on.

At the same time, this mechanism provides a means of simultaneously allocating PIO memory, ensuring that sufficient memory is available on a given PIO block and atomically allocating it if it is available.

Freeing state machines is provided for, but if the user wishes to free PIO memory they must do so manually with pio::free-piomem.

Last but not least, for the sake of convenience a means of installing a PIO program into all the allocated state machines at once is provided.

pio-pool module

The pio-pool module contains the following words:

x-invalid-sm-count

( – )

This exception is raised if the user attempts to allocate fewer than 1 or greater than 4 PIO state machines.

x-unable-allocate-pio/sm

( – )

This exception is raised if a PIO/state machine word fails for any reason, e.g. insufficient free state machines on any single PIO block and/or no PIO block with sufficient free state machines has adequate PIO memory available.

allocate-pio-sms

( sm-count – smn … sm0 pio )

Allocate 1 to 4 state machines on a single PIO block and return the state machine indices and the PIO block.

allocate-pio-sms-w-piomem

( size sm-count – smn … sm0 base pio )

Allocate 1 to 4 state machines on a single PIO block, atomically allocating the specified PIO program size in that PIO block’s memory (ensuring that the selected PIO block has sufficient space in the process), and returning the state machine indices, the allocated PIO memory base address, and the PIO block.

allocate-pio-sms-w-prog

( program sm-count – smn … sm0 base pio )

Allocate 1 to 4 state machines on a single PIO block, atomically allocating the specified PIO program’s size in that PIO block’s memory (ensuring that the selected PIO block has sufficient space in the process), installing the PIO program into the selected PIO block’s memory, configuring the allocated state machines to execute the PIO program, and returning the state machine indices, the allocated PIO memory base address, and the PIO block.

free-pio-sm

( sm pio – )

Free a single state machine for a specified PIO block.

Pool Words

Pools in zeptoforth are created by the user and consist of discretes blocks that are allocated and freed individual as wholes. There is by default no global pool, and pools created by the user are specifically not concurrency-safe; to make them concurrency-safe one must wrap them in locks, and because of the overhead this would impose, this is not done so by default. Allocating and freeing blocks in pools occurs in constant time and are fast, unlike allocation, resizing, and freeing in heaps

pool

The following words are in pool:

pool-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of a pool header in bytes.

init-pool

( block-size addr – )

Initialize a pool at addr with the given block size of block-size bytes. Note that no space for storing blocks is available in a pool when it is first initialized; to add memory to a pool use add-pool.

add-pool

( addr bytes pool – )

Add memory starting at addr of size bytes to pool as discrete blocks; only a multiple of the block size of the pool will be added to the pool, so if bytes is not a multiple of said block size not all of the space in the memory provided will be used.

allocate-pool

( pool – addr )

Allocate a block in pool and return its address. If no blocks are available in the pool, x-allocate-failed is raised.

free-pool

( addr pool – )

Free a block at addr in pool, making it available to future allocation.

pool-block-size

( pool – bytes )

Get the block size of a pool.

pool-free-count

( pool – count )

Get the number of free blocks in a pool.

pool-total-count

( pool – count )

Get the total number of blocks in a pool.

x-allocate-failed

( – )

The exception raised if block allocation fails.

PSRAM words

The rp2350 platform optionally supports Quad SPI pseudo-static RAM (PSRAM for short) tied to a GPIO selected as QMI CS1n. PSRAM when enabled is transparent to the user and may be arbitrarily accessed as a block of RAM. PSRAM starts at psram-base and is psram-size bytes in size once enabled.

Note that PSRAM is slower than SRAM, being external to the RP2350 and tied to the RP2350 through a Quad SPI interface, so one should use SRAM for things which are performance-critical, especially since it competes with Quad SPI flash for XIP cache space.

Only certain GPIO’s may be used for the QMI CS1n pin. These are GPIO’s 0, 8, 19, and 47. Note that many boards with RP2350B chips such as the Pimoroni Pico Plus 2 use GPIO 47 for this purpose.

forth

The following words in this module pertain to PSRAM usage:

init-psram

( psram-cs-pin – )

Initialize PSRAM with QMI CS1n set to GPIO psram-cs-pin, which must be one of 0, 8, 19, or 47 or otherwise x-invalid-qmi-cs1n-pin will be raised. If no PSRAM is available tied to the selected GPIO, x-no-psram will be raised.

psram-size

( – bytes )

Get the number of bytes of PSRAM. This is initialized on boot to 0, and is set by init-psram.

psram-base

( – addr )

Get the base address of PSRAM.

x-invalid-qmi-cs1n-pin

( – )

The exception raised if init-psram is called with an invalid QMI CS1n GPIO index.

x-no-psram

( – )

The exception raised if no PSRAM is available on the selected QMI CS1n GPIO.

Pulse Width Modulation Words

The RP2040 (which is in the Raspberry Pi Pico) has support for Pulse Width Modulation (PWM for short), which includes a counter capability. There are eight PWM “slices”, each of which have pair of GPIO pins as outputs, pins A and B, and pin B can also be used as an input. Also, each of the PWM slices, aside from PWM slice 7, maps to four separate GPIO pins, two of which are A pins and two of which are B pins (PWM slice 7 only maps to one A pin and one B pin).

Each PWM slice is associated with a counter value and a top value at which the counter wraps back to zero. Also, the A and B outputs each have a compare value at which their output transitions from high to low. Note that PWM slices have a “phase correct” mode which modifies this functionality so that the phase of a PWM output does not change with changes to its compare value.

PWM slices have a clock divider which divides the system clock by an integral value, from 1 to 255, plus a fractional value, of 0 to 15 divided by 16.

PWM slices have four different primary modes. One is free-running mode, where the counter increases by one each cycle. Another is gating mode, where the counter increases by one each cycle the B input of the PWM slice is high. Another is risng-edge mode, where the counter increases by one for each rising edge detected on the B input of the PWM slice. And last but not least, there is falling-edge mode, where the counter increase by one for each falling edge detected on the B input of the PWM slice.

When a PWM slice’s counter reaches its top value, an interrupt can be raised. All PWM slices share the same IRQ. They have separate flags indicating their interrupt status, which can be cleared independent of one another, and interrupts can be enabled and disabled independently of each of them.

Last but not least, PWM slices’ A and B outputs can be inverted independent of one another.

pwm

The following words are in the pwm module:

x-out-of-range-pwm

( – )

Out of range PWM index exception.

x-out-of-range-clock-div

( – )

Out of range clock divisor exception.

x-out-of-range-counter

( – )

Out of range counter value exception.

x-out-of-range-compare

( – )

Out of range compare value exception.

x-out-of-range-top

( – )

Out of range top value exception.

pwm-pin

( pin – )

Set a pin as a PWM pin.

pwm-vector!

( xt – )

Set PWM IRQ handler.

enable-pwm

( bits – )

Enable any set of slices, expressed as bits from 0 to 7.

disable-pwm

( bits – )

Disable any set of slices, expressed as bits from 0 to 7.

enable-pwm-int

( bits – )

Enable interrupts for any set of slices, expressed as bits from 0 to 7.

disable-pwm-int

( bits – )

Disable interrupts for any set of slices, expressed as bits from 0 to 7.

clear-pwm-int

( bits – )

Clear an interrupt for any set of slices, expressed as bits from 0 to 7.

pwm-int@

( – bits )

Get the interrupt state for all slices, expressed as one bit per slice from 0 to 7.

clear-pwm-pending

( – )

Clear pending PWM interrupt.

advance-pwm-phase

( index – )

Advance the phase of a running counter by 1 count.

retard-pwm-phase

( index – )

Retard the phase of a running counter by 1 count.

free-running-pwm

( index – )

Set a slice to be free-running.

gated-pwm

( index – )

Set a slice to be gated by the PWM B pin.

rising-edge-pwm

( index – )

Set a slice to advance with each rising eddge of the PWM B pin.

falling-edge-pwm

( index – )

Set a slice to advance with each falling edge of the PWM B pin.

pwm-invert-b!

( state index – )

Set invert PWM output B for a slice.

pwm-invert-a!

( state index – )

Set invert PWM output A for a slice.

pwm-phase-correct!

( state index – )

Set phase-correct modulation for a slice.

pwm-clock-div!

( fract int index – )

Set clock frequency divisor; int is the integral portion from 1 to 255 and fract is the fractional portion from 0 to 15.

pwm-counter-compare-b!

( value index – )

Set the PWM output B for a slice counter compare value.

pwm-counter-compare-a!

( value index – )

Set the PWM output A for a slice counter compare value.

pwm-top!

( value index – )

Set the slice counter wrap value.

pwm-counter!

( value index – )

Set the slice counter value.

pwm-counter@

( index – value )

Get the slice counter value.

Quad SPI words

The Quad SPI interface is written for the STM32F746 DISCOVERY board. It maps Quad SPI flash to the addressing space at qspi-base. It also provides means for writing bytes, halfwords, words, and arbitrary buffers containing bytes to flash and erasing 4K and 32K subsectors, 64K sectors, and the entire flash. Note that even though internally they require turning off memory-mapped Quad SPI mode, it is automatically turned back on when they are complete, and they are hidden from all other tasks (however they significantly impact realtime performance due to being slow while requiring interrupts to be turned off).

qspi

The following words are in qspi:

qspi-base

( – addr )

Returns the base address of the Quad SPI memory mapped space.

qspi-size

( – bytes )

Returns the size of the Quad SPI flash space in bytes.

qspi-inited?

( – flag )

Returns whether Quad SPI is initialized - should always be true after system initialization.

map-qspi-enabled?

( – flag )

Returns whether mapping Quad SPI to memory is enabled - should always be true after system initialization.

x-invalid-qspi-addr

( – )

Invalid Quad SPI address exception.

qspi!

( x addr – )

Writes a 32-bit value in little-endian order to Quad SPI flash at the address corresponding to the specified address in memory-mapped Quad SPI space; note that it has to be 32-bit aligned.

hqspi!

( h addr – )

Writes a 16-bit value in little-endian order to Quad SPI flash at the address corresponding to the specified address in memory-mapped Quad SPI space; note that it has to be 16-bit aligned.

bqspi!

( b addr – )

Writes a 8-bit value to Quad SPI flash at the address corresponding to the specified address in memory-mapped Quad SPI space; note that it has to be 16-bit aligned.

mass-qspi!

( data-addr bytes addr – )

Writes an arbitrary number of bytes in the provided buffer to Quad SPIs starting at the specified address in memory-mapped Quad SPI space; note the data can be larger than a write page (and can therefore cross write page boundaries) despite the underlying hardware not allowing this due to this case being handled in sofotware.

erase-qspi-4k-subsector

( addr – )

Erase a 4K flash subsector containing the specified address in memory-mapped Quad SPI space.

erase-qspi-32k-subsector

( addr – )

Erase a 32K flash subsector containing the specified address in memory-mapped Quad SPI space.

erase-qspi-sector

( addr – )

Erase a 64K flash sector containing the specified address in memory-mapped Quad SPI space.

erase-qspi-bulk

( – )

Erase the entire contents of Quad SPI flash.

Bidirectional Channel Words

A bidirectional channel is a bidirectional means of communicating data between two different tasks, involving interlocking messages sent to tasks listening on them followed by replies sent synchronously back to original sending tasks by the receiving tasks. Bidirectional channels are not buffered queues; provided another task is listening to a bidirectional channel, sending on a bidirectional channel immediately transfers control to the receiving task and sends the sending task to the end of the scheduling ring. Only a single copy is done when transferring data from the sending task to the receiving task.

Tasks attempting to send on bidirectional channels first check whether there is a queued task waiting to receive on the bidirectional channel; if there are tasks queued to receive, the first task queued is dequeued, the sending task’s buffer is copied into the receiving task’s buffer, and the receiving task is readied. If no tasks are queued to receive, the sending task is queued to send on the bidirectional channel and is blocked.

Tasks attempting to receive on bidirectional channels first check whether there is a queued task waiting to send on the bidirectional channel; if there are tasks queued to send, the first task queued is dequeued, the sending task’s buffer is copied into the receiving task’s buffer, and the sending task is readied. If no tasks are queued to send, the receiving task is queued to receive on the bidirectional channel and is blocked.

Both the send queues and receive queues are ordered first by task priority and second by the order in which tasks were added to them, with tasks of higher priority and tasks added earlier coming first.

Once a task receives a message on a bidirectional channel, the bidirectional channel is put into a state where it is pending a reply. No other messages will be sent over the bidirectional channel until the task which received the message sends a reply back to the task which had originally sent on the bidirectional channel. Like the original message sent from the sending task to the receiving task, no data is buffered in a reply but rather the reply data is copied directly from the buffer provided by the replying task to the reply buffer provided by the original sending task.

Bidirectional channels can be created anywhere in memory; they are not dependent upon any allocation mechanism. Therefore they can be put into alloted memory in the dictionary or into allocated memory in the heap.

rchan

The following words are in rchan:

x-rchan-closed

( – )

The bidirectional channel closed exception.

x-reply-pending

( – )

This exception is raised if a bidirectional channel is replied to after it has already been replied to and before the original sending task awaiting for a reply has had the chance to handle the reply

rchan-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of an bidirectional channel in bytes.

init-rchan

( addr – )

Initialize a bidirectional channel starting at the specified address.

close-rchan

( rchan – )

Close a bidirectional channel. Pending sends and receives will be aborted with the exception x-rchan-closed.

reopen-rchan

( rchan – )

Reopen a bidirectional channel.

rchan-closed?

( rchan – closed )

Get whether a bidirectional channel is closed.

send-rchan

( send-addr send-bytes reply-addr reply-bytes rchan – reply-bytes’ )

Send message with a buffer send-addr with size send-bytes in bytes as a payload over a bidirectional channel. Block until another task replies to the message; if a task is already waiting for a message, transfer control to it. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the buffer size of the bidirectional channel is smaller than the data provided, and padded with zeros if it is larger. In turn, the reply provided by the receiving task is copied into the provided reply buffer reply-addr with the size reply-bytes in bytes, and the actual size in bytes of the reply is returned. Note that this must not be called within a critical section.

recv-rchan

( addr bytes rchan – recv-bytes )

Receive message with a buffer addr with size bytes in bytes as a payload over a bidirectional channel. Block until another task sends a message. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the bufer size of the bidirectional channel; the number of bytes copied is returned. At this point the bidirectional channel is in a state where it is waiting for a reply; the sending task will only be readied once a reply is provided with reply-rchan. Note that this must not be called within a critical section. Note that the task for which a bidirectional channel is awaiting a reply following a receive cannot receive from that bidirectional channel; if this is attenpted x-rchan-wait-reply is raised.

reply-rchan

( addr bytes rchan – )

Reply to a bidirectional channel which the current task had received a message from with the data in buffer addr with size bytes in bytes. This data is copied into the reply buffer of the original sending task, truncated to the size of the sending task’s reply buffer. Note that if no task is waiting for a reply, the reply is discarded silently; this is necessary due to the possibility of sending tasks timing out prior to receiving their reply.

Realtime Clock (RTC) Words

zeptoforth has support for reading and setting the realtime clock (RTC) on the Raspberry Pi Pico, both for keeping track of the date and time and for triggering an alarm.

Note that the Raspberry Pi Pico’s RTC’s value is not preserved across resets, even if power is applied, so each time it is reset the RTC’s value must be provided a value before it can be useful. It is initialized on bootup to Thursday, 1 January 1970 00:00:00, and is enabled on boot.

The alarm functionality allows triggering an alarm interrupt at a given combination of second, minute, hour, day of the week, day, month, and/or year values. Note that the alarm interrupt must either reset the alarm date/time to a new one or clear the alarm or otherwise it will be repeatedly triggered, which in most use cases is undesirable.

Date time values are validated when provided, except that year values of -1 and values for other fields of $FF are ignored during validation, as they are explicit non-values used for setting a subset of RTC fields or matching against a subset of RTC fields.

Also provided is code for formatting date/times as strings and printing them to the console, for convenience’s sake.

Note that a subset of these words are provided for platforms other than the Raspberry Pi Pico, specifically all of these words aside from enable-rtc, disable-rtc, date-time!, simple-date-time!, set-rtc-alarm, and clear-rtc-alarm.

rtc

The following words are in the rtc module:

date-time-size

( – bytes )

This returns the size of a date/time structure in bytes.

date-time-year

( date-time – addr )

This returns the address of a cell in a date/time containing a year, from 0 to 4095, or when not setting a year or not matching against a year, -1

date-time-month

( date-time – c-addr )

This returns the address of a byte in a date/time containing a month, from 1 to 12, or when not setting a month or not matching against a month, 255

date-time-day

( date-time – c-addr )

This returns the address of a byte in a date/time containing a day, from 1 to any of 28, 29, 30, or 31 depending on the month and year, or when not setting a day or not matching against a day, 255

date-time-dotw

( date-time – c-addr )

This returns the address of a byte in a date/time containing a day of the week, from 0 representing Sunday to 6 representing Saturday, or when not setting a day of the week or not matching against a day of the week, 255.

date-time-hour

( date-time – c-addr )

This returns the address of a byte in a date/time containing an hour, from 0 to 23, or when not setting an hour or not matching against an hour, 255.

date-time-minute

( date-time – c-addr )

This returns the address of a byte in a date/time containing a minute, from 0 to 59, or when not setting a minute or not matching against a minute, 255.

date-time-second

( date-time – c-addr )

This returns the address of a byte in a date/time containing a second, from 0 to 59, or when not setting a second or not matching against a second, 255.

enable-rtc

( – )

Enable the realtime clock. (Note that it is enabled by default.)

disable-rtc

( – )

Disable the realtime clock.

date-time-equal?

( date-time0 date-time1 – equal? )

Check whether two date-times are equal (ignoring the day of the week).

date-time@

( date-time – )

Get the current date/time.

date-time!

( date-time – )

Set the current date/time.

simple-date-time!

( year month day hour minute second – )

A convenience word to the current date/time at once, automatically calculating the day of the week. The arguments have the same meanings, respectively, as the date-time-year, date-time-month, date-time-day, date-time-hour, date-time-minute, and date-time-second of a date/time structure except that for all of these, not just the year, may have values of -1 to indicate unchanged values. Also, note that if year is -1, month is -1 or 255, or day is -1 or 255, the day of the week is not changed.

set-rtc-alarm

( date-time xt – )

Set xt to execute as an RTC alarm interrupt handler at date-time, ignoring a year field of -1 and any of the other fields of 255. Note that when xt is executed it must reset the RTC alarm to a new date/time or clear the RTC alarm or else it will be triggered repeatedly.

clear-rtc-alarm

( – )

Clear the RTC alarm.

dotw-name

( dotw – c-addr u )

Get the name of a day of the week.

month-name

( month – c-addr u )

Get the name of a month.

max-date-time-format-size

( – bytes )

Get the maximum size in bytes of a date formated with format-date-time.

format-date-time

( c-addr date-time – c-addr u )

Format date-time as a string starting at c-addr, and return the resulting string as the pair c-addr u.

date-time.

( date-time – )

Print a date/time as formatted with format-date-time.

get-dotw

( date-time – dotw )

Calculate the day of the week for a date/time, ignoring its day of the week field; 0 is Sunday and 6 is Saturday. Note that if the date-time-year field of date-time is -1, the date-time-month field of date-time is 255, or the date-time-day field of date-time is 255, 255 will be returned for the day of the week.

update-dotw

( date-time )

Update the day of the week for a date/time, ignoring its preexisting day of the week field. Note that if the date-time-year field of date-time is -1, the date-time-month field of date-time is 255, or the date-time-day field of date-time is 255, 255 will be set for the day of the week.

convert-secs-since-1970

( seconds date-time – )

Set a day-time with seconds from 1970-01-01 00:00:00 UTC.

Simple channel Words

A simple channel is a monodirectional means of communicating data, as arbitrary-sized blocks of data, between two or more different tasks and/or interrupt service routines. Simple channels form a fixed-size queue onto which data is sent on one end and data is received on the other. Any task which attempts to send data on a full simple channel, or receive data on an empty simple channel, will be suspended until either data is received from the simple channel, or data is sent to the simple channel, respectively, unless non-blocking operations are used, where then x-would-block (declared in task) is raised instead of blocking. Note that non-blocking simple channel routines are specifically interrupt service routine-safe, unlike other channel constructs provided by zeptoforth.

Simple channels can be created anywhere in memory; they are not dependent upon any allocation mechanism. Therefore they can be put into alloted memory in the dictionary or into allocated memory in the heap. Note that the size of a simple channel for a given element size and element count may be calculated with schan-size.

schan

The following words are in schan:

x-schan-closed

( – )

Simple channel closed exception. Raised on attempting to send to a closed simple channel or when trying to receive on an empty closed simple channel.

schan-full?

( schan – flag )

Get whether a simple channel is full.

schan-empty?

( schan – flag )

Get whether a simple channel is empty.

schan-size

( element-bytes element-count – total-bytes )

Get the size in memory for a simple channel with a specified element size in bytes and element count.

init-schan

( element-bytes element-count addr – )

Initialize a simple channel starting at the specified address with the element size and element count. The element-bytes and element-count should be the same as when they were passed to schan-size when alloting or allocating the memory whose starting address is passed in.

close-schan

( schan – )

Close a simple channel. Raise x-schan-closed for all pending sending tasks or for all pending receiving tasks if the simple channel is empty.

reopen-schan

( schan – )

Reopen a simple channel.

schan-closed?

( schan – closed )

Get whether a simple channel is closed.

send-schan

( addr bytes schan – )

Send message with a buffer as a payload over a simple channel. Block until another task receives the message if the simple channel is full. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the buffer size of the simple channel is smaller than the data provided, and padded with zeros if it is larger. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

recv-schan

( addr bytes schan – recv-bytes )

Receive message into a buffer from a simple channel. Block until another task sends a message if the simple channel is empty. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the simple channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-schan

( addr bytes schan – addr peek-bytes )

Peek the oldest message into a buffer from a simple channel, without popping it from the simple channel’s queue. Block until another task sends a message if the simple channel is empty. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the simple channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-schan

( schan – )

Skip the most oldest message in a simple channel. Block until another task sends a message if the simple channel is empty. Note that no copying takes place, making this faster than receiving a message. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

send-schan-no-block

( addr bytes schan – )

Send message with a buffer as a payload over a simple channel. If the simple channel is full, or if another task or interrupt service rouine is attempting to send on the same simple channel simultaneously, x-would-block is raised. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the buffer size of the simple channel is smaller than the data provided, and padded with zeros if it is larger. This is safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

recv-schan-no-block

( addr bytes schan – recv-bytes )

Receive message into a buffer from a simple channel. If the simple channel is empty, or if another task or interrupt service rouine is attempting to receive on the same simple channel simultaneously, x-would-block is raised. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the simple channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-schan-no-block

( addr bytes schan – addr peek-bytes )

Peek the oldest message into a buffer from a simple channel, without popping it from the simple channel’s queue. If the simple channel is empty, or if another task or interrupt service rouine is attempting to receive on the same simple channel simultaneously, x-would-block is raised. Note that the buffer is copied, and will be truncated if the provided buffer is smaller than the buffer size of the simple channel, and padded with zeros if it is larger; the number of bytes copied is returned. This is safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-schan-no-block

( schan – )

Skip the most oldest message in a simple channel. If the simple channel is empty, or if another task or interrupt service rouine is attempting to receive on the same simple channel simultaneously, x-would-block is raised. Note that no copying takes place, making this faster than receiving a message. This is safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

Simple Lock Words

A simple lock enforces mutual exclusion, typically with regard to control of a resource, between multiple tasks. Unlike a normal lock, it does not establish a queue of multiple waiting tasks, but rather no particular order is established for which task claims the lock when multiple tasks are waiting on the lock to be released by another task. Simple locks are optimized for speed when claiming locks that are only held for very short periods of time, and particularly on multicore systems they should not be held for long because other tasks which attempt to claim them on other cores will spinwait until the lock is freed. Simple locks provide no means of avoiding priority inversion, which is another reason for avoiding holding them for long. Also, no means are provided to avoid double locking, so if a task double locks a simple lock it will hang forever until it is killed.

slock

The following words are in slock:

slock-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of a simple lock in bytes.

init-slock

( addr – )

Initialize a simple lock starting at the specified address addr; note that it must be slock-size bytes in size.

try-claim-slock

( slock – success? )

Attempt to claim a simple lock slock and return whether claiming it was successful.

claim-slock

( slock – )

Attempt to claim a simple lock slock; if the simple lock is already held, continually attempt to claim the simple lock until it can be successfully claimed. In that case, if the simple lock is held by another task on the same core as the task attempting to claim it, give up the processor after each unsuccessful attempt to claim the simple lock; if it is held by another task on a different core, spinwait instead.

release-slock

( slock – )

Release a simple lock slock. If other tasks are waiting to claim the simple lock, the first one to attempt to claim it next will claim it.

with-slock

( xt slock – )

Execute an xt xt with a given simple lock slock locked while it executes, unlocking it afterwards. If an exception is raised by xt, unlock lock and then re-raise the exception.

SPI Words

There are a number of words for controlling SPI peripherals available on each of the supported microcontrollers. These are as follows:

Note that spi values as mentioned below vary between the different supported platforms. The following applies:

On the RP2040 and RP2350 the available spi values are 0 and 1.

On the STM32F411 the available spi values are 1 through 5.

On the STM32F407 the available spi values are 1 through 3.

On the STM32L476 the available spi values are 1 through 3.

On the STM32F746 the available spi values are 1 through 6.

spi

These words are in the spi module:

All platforms

enable-spi

( spi – )

Enable an SPI peripheral.

disable-spi

( spi – )

Disable an SPI peripheral. Note that SPI peripherals are disabled by default.

enable-spi-tx

( spi – )

Enable SPI peripheral transmit.

disable-spi-tx

( spi – )

Disable SPI peripheral transmit.

master-spi

( spi – )

Set an SPI peripheral to be a master. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

slave-spi

( spi – )

Set an SPI peripheral to be a slave. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

spi-baud!

( baud spi – )

Set the baud of a master SPI peripheral. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

motorola-spi

( sph spo spi – )

Set the protocol of an SPI peripheral to Motorola SPI, with SPO/CPOL set to spo and SPH/CPHA set to sph. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

ti-ss-spi

( spi – )

Set the protocol of an SPI peripheral to TI synchronous serial. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

spi-data-size!

( data-size spi – )

Set the word size of an SPI peripheral to data-size bits; on the RP2040 and RP2350, STM32L476, and STM32F746 any value from 4 to 16 is permitted, whereas on the STM32F407 and STM32F411 only 8 and 16 are permitted. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

>spi

( c spi – )

Emit a word to an SPI peripheral.

spi>

( spi – c )

Read a word from an SPI peripheral.

buffer>spi

( addr bytes spi – )

Write a buffer of data to an SPI peripheral as a master, discarding the data returned by the slave.

spi>buffer

( add bytes filler spi – )

Read a buffer of data from an SPI peripheral as a master, transmitting a filler for each unit of data sent to the slave.

>spi?

( spi – flag )

Get whether an SPI peripheral is ready to emit a word.

spi>?

( spi – flag )

Get whether a word is ready to be read from an SPI peripheral.

drain-spi

( spi – )

Empty an SPI peripheral’s receive buffer.

flush-spi

( spi – )

Flush an SPI peripheral’s transmit buffer.

spi-alternate

( spi – )

The alternate function for a given SPI peripheral. Note that using spi-pin is recommended as some SPI peripherals may have multiple alternate functions in practice depending on the particular pin.

spi-pin

( spi pin – )

Set the alternate function for pin to configure it for spi.

spi-rx-handler!

( xt spi – )

Set an SPI RX handler called when the SPI interrupt is called for RX data. Note that this may not be called if spi> is called before the SPI interrupt has the chance to be invoked. A value of 0 indicates no handler.

x-invalid-spi

( – )

Invalid SPI peripheral exception.

x-invalid-spi-clock

( – )

Invalid SPI clock setting exception.

x-invalid-spi-data-size

( – )

Invalid SPI data size setting exception.

RP2040 and RP2350 only

enable-spi-loopback

( spi – )

Enable SPI loopback mode for an SPI peripheral.

disable-spi-loopback

( spi – )

Disable SPI loopback mdoe for an SPI peripheral.

natl-microwire-spi

( spi – )

Set the protocol of the SPI peripheral to National Semiconductor Microwire.

STM32F407, STM32F411, STM32L476, and STM32F746 only

msb-first-spi

( spi – )

Set an SPI peripheral to have MSB-first data. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

lsb-first-spi

( spi – )

Set an SPI peripheral to have LSB-first data. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

enable-spi-ssm

( spi – )

Enable SPI software slave management by master SPI peripherals. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

disable-spi-ssm

( spi – )

Disable SPI software slave management by master SPI peripherals. This must be done with the SPI peripheral disabled.

spi-ssm!

( ssi spi – )

Set the software slave management selection for master SPI peripherals.

1-line-spi

( spi – )

Set an SPI peripheral to one-wire mode.

2-line-spi

( spi – )

Set an SPI peripheral to two-wire mode (the default).

1-line-spi-in

( spi – )

Set the single wire in one-wire mode to be an input.

1-line-spi-out

( spi – )

Set the single wire in one-wire mode to be an output.

RP2040-only words

buffer>spi-raw-dma

( addr bytes dma1 dma0 spi – last-data )

Write a buffer of data to an SPI peripheral as a master, discarding the data returned by the slave. This word uses the DMA channels dma0 and dma1, and returns the last data read from the SPI peripheral.

spi>buffer-raw-dma

( add bytes filler dma1 dma0 spi – )

Read a buffer of data from an SPI peripheral as a master, transmitting a filler for unit of data sent to the slave. This word uses the DMA channels dma0 and dma1.

Stream Words

A stream is a monodirectional means of communicating data, as a fixed-size queue of bytes which may be accessed without any kind of message boundaries. Streams can be sent to and received from using both blocking operations, which when sending may wait to send entire buffers at once or may allow sending data in parts until all the data is sent, and when receiving/peeking/skipping may wait until a non-zero amount of data is available, and non-blocking operations, which when sending may raise x-would-block (declared in task) if blocking would occur or maysend only part of the buffer provided, and when receiving/peeking/skipping may return a zero byte count.

Streams can be created anywhere in memory; they are not dependent upon any allocation mechanism. Therefore they can be put in alloted memory in the dictionary or into allocated memory in the heap. Note that the size of a stream for a given data size may be calculated with stream-size.

stream

The following words are in stream:

x-stream-closed

( – )

Stream closed exception. Raised on attempting to send to a closed stream or when trying to receive on an empty closed stream.

x-stream-data-too-big

( – )

Data being sent on a stream with send-stream is larger than the size of the stream exception.

stream-full?

( stream – flag )

Get whether a stream is full.

stream-empty?

( stream – flag )

Get whether a stream is empty.

stream-size

( data-bytes – total-bytes )

Get the size in memory for a stream with a specified data size in bytes.

init-stream

( data-bytes addr – )

Initialize a stream starting at he specified address with the specified data size in bytes data-bytes. data-bytes should be the same as the value passed to stream-size when alloting or allocating the memory whose starting address is passed in.

close-stream

( stream – )

Close a stream. Raise x-stream-closed for all pending sending tasks or for all pending receiving tasks if the stream is empty.

reopen-stream

( stream – )

Reopen a stream.

stream-closed?

( stream – closed )

Get whether a stream is closed.

send-stream

( addr bytes stream – )

Send data with a buffer to a stream. Block until there is enough space available in the stream to add the entire buffer of data. Note that the data is copied. x-stream-data-too-big is raised if bytes is greater than the data size of the stream. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

send-stream-parts

( addr bytes stream – )

Send data with a buffer to a stream. Block until there is all the data is sent, adding the data incrementally as space becomes available in the stream. Note that if sending times out, the data may be left partially sent. Note that the data is copied. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critcal section.

recv-stream

( addr bytes stream – recv-bytes )

Receive data into a buffer from a stream. Block until data becomes available in the stream. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower than the byte count passed in. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

recv-stream-min

( addr bytes min-bytes stream – recv-bytes )

Receive at least a minimum number of bytes into a buffer from a stream. Block until the minimum number of bytes become available. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower than the buffer size passed in, even though it will always be equal to or greater than the minimum byte count. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-stream

( addr bytes stream – peek-bytes )

Peek data into a buffer from a stream, without removing it from the stream. Block until data becomes available in the stream. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower than the byte count passed in. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-stream-min

( addr bytes min-bytes tream – peek-bytes )

Peek at least a minimum number of bytes into a buffer from a stream, without removing them from the stream. Block until the minimum number of bytes become available. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower than the buffer size passed in, even though it will always be equal to or greater than the minimum byte count. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-stream

( bytes stream – skip-bytes )

Skip data in a stream, removing it from the stream without copying it. Block until data becomes available in the stream. Note that less data may be skipped than the byte count provided, and the returned byte count is the number of bytes actually skipped. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-stream-min

( bytes min-bytes stream – skip bytes )

Skip at least a minimum number of bytes in a stream, removing them from the stream without copying them. Block until the minimum number of bytes become available. Note that less data may be skipped than the byte count bytes, even though it will always be equal or greater than the minimum byte count min-bytes; the returned byte count is the number of bytes actually skipped. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

send-stream-no-block

( addr bytes stream – )

Send data with a buffer to a stream. If there is insufficient space available in the stream to copy the entire buffer, x-would-block is raised. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

send-stream-partial-no-block

( addr bytes stream – send-bytes )

Send data with a buffer to a stream. Only as much data as there is space for inthe stream is sent; the remaining data is omitted. The actual number of bytes sent is returned. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

recv-stream-no-block

( addr bytes stream – recv-bytes )

Receive data into a buffer from a stream. If no data is available, return a byte count of zero. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower than the byte count passed in. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

recv-stream-min-no-block

( addr bytes min-bytes stream – recv-bytes )

Receive at least a minimum number of bytes from a stream. If the minimum number of bytes is not available, receive no bytes and return a byte count of zero. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower than the byte count bytes passed in. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-stream-no-block

( addr bytes stream – peek-bytes )

Peek data into a buffer from a stream, without removing it from the stream. if no data is available, return a byte count of zero. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower than the byte count passed in. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

peek-stream-min-no-block

( addr bytes min-bytes stream – peek-bytes )

Peek at least a minimum number of bytes from a stream, without removing them from the stream. If the minimum number of bytes is not available, peek no bytes and return a byte count of zero. Note that only as much data is available is copied, and the returned byte count may be lower th an the byte count bytes passed in. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-stream-no-block

( bytes stream – skip-bytes )

Skip data in a stream, removing it from the stream without copying it. If no data is available, return a byte count of zero. Note that less data may be skipped than the byte count provided, and the returned byte count is the number of bytes actually skipped. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

skip-stream-min-no-block

( bytes min-bytes stream – skip-bytes )

Skip at least a minimum number of bytes in a stream, removing them from the stream without copying them. If the minimum number of bytes is not available, skip no bytes and return a byte count of zero. Note that less data may be skipped by thane byte count bytes provided, and the returned byte count is the number of bytes actually skipped. This is not safe to call within an interrupt service routine or a critical section.

Task Pool words

Task pools provide a means of managing multiple tasks and dynamically creating and destroying them. Note that the total number of task that may exist at any one time is fixed, but the number of executing tasks may be of any number less than or equal to that at any point in time.

task-pool

The following words are in task-pool:

x-no-task-available

( – )

Exception raised if one attempts to spawn a task from a task pool and no tasks are available.

spawn-from-task-pool

( xn … x0 count xt task-pool – task )

Spawn a task from a task pool, if a task is available, or raise x-no-task-available if no tasks are available. xn through x0 are parameters to pass to the xt when executed, and count is the number of such parameters.

task-pool-free

( task-pool – count )

Get the number of free tasks in a task pool.

init-task-pool

( dict-size stack-size rstack-size count addr – )

Initialize a task pool at addr, with count tasks, each with stack-size stack size, rstack-size return stack size, and dict-size dictionary size; note that stack-size, rstack-size, and dict-size are rounded up to the nearest four bytes. These tasks are terminated initially, and are free to be spawned as needed.

task-pool-size

( count – bytes )

Get the size (excluding the tasks themselves) taken up by a task pool with count tasks; this size should be used for alloting the block of memory to be passed to init-task-pool

Temporary Buffer Words

Temporary buffers are circular buffers for allocating temporary data. Temporarily allocated space should not be relied upon to store data indefinitely, because they reallocate space allocated to old buffers when no more space for continguous blocks of memory are available.

temp

The following words are in temp.

x-data-too-big

( – )

An exception raised when the size of the data requested to be allocated is larger than the size of the temporary buffer’s total space.

temp-size

( data-bytes – bytes )

Get the size of a temporary buffer with a given data size.

init-temp

( data-bytes addr – )

Initialize a temporary buffer with a given data size at the specified address. Note that the amount of space returned by temp-size for the given data size should be alloted or allocated for the temporary buffer.

allocate-temp

( bytes temp – addr )

Allocate temporary space of a given data size for a given temporary buffer. If the data size is larger than the temporary buffer’s total data size, x-data-too-big is raised.

Testing Words

Stack Testing

Stack testing involves checking the stack pointer before and after the code being tested is executed, and testing for the change in the stack pointer as well as matching the values put on the stack by the code being tested against the values expected. By its very nature this code is applied a task-specific level but can be used in different tasks simultaneously. This code is not part of the prebuilt binaries, but rather is in test/common/stack.fs and may be used both compiled to flash and compiled to RAM.

forth

The following words are in forth.

stack-fail-hook

stack-fail-hook specifies an xt to be executed, if set to a value other than 0, when a stack test fails. By default this is set to 0.

x-stack-fail

( – )

x-stack-fail is an exception raised when }t detects a stack position mismatch relative to the stack pointer recorded by t{ and the number of cells on the stack passed into it. The purpose of this exception is that the stack pointer is unknown, so the only way to recover from it is by raising an exception.

t{

( – ) ( R: – sp )

This word saves the current stack pointer on the return stack for it to be used later by }t.

}t

( x1 … xn y1 … yn u – ) ( R: old-sp – )

This word checks that the current stack position is two times u cells greater than the old stack position recorded on the return stack; if this is not the case the xt stored in stack-fail-hook is executed, if it is not 0, and then x-stack-fail is raised. If this is the case each value xi is matched against its corresponding value yi, if any one of these does not match, then the xt stored in stack-fail-hook is executed if it is not 0.

Emit Capture Testing

Emit capture testing involves installing a hook into emit transparently, and using this to capture and test each byte emitted against specified rules without interfering with the operation of the system. This is done in a transparently multitasking-friendly manner, and can be used to test behavior spread across multiple tasks without any extra work being needed on the programmer’s part. This code is not part of the prebuilt binaries, but rather is in test/common/capture.fs and may be used both compiled to flash and compiled to RAM.

forth

The following words are in forth.

capture-fail-hook

capture-fail-hook specifies an xt to be executed, if set to a value other than 0, when an emit capture test fails. By default this is set to 0.

enable-capture

( – )

This word enables emit capture testing.

disable-capture

( – )

This word disables emit capture testing.

no-capture

( xt – )

This word temporarily disables emit capture testing, and then executes xt, afterwards enabling emit capture testing if it had been previously enabled.

x-capture-full

( – )

This word is the exception raised when the emit capture test buffer is full and the user attempts to add another emit capture test.

clear-capture

( – )

This word clears the emit capture test buffer, effectively disabling emit capture test until another emit capture test is added.

add-match-capture

( b-addr bytes xt – )

This word adds a matching emit capture test, which fails unless each character in the specified string is matched in order. xt is an xt which is executed when either the matching emit capture test fails, where then it is passed false, or when the matching emit capture test is successfully completed, where then it is passed true, unless it is set to 0, where then it is ignored.

add-skip-capture

( b-addr bytes limit xt – )

This word adds a skipping emit capture test, which fails if more than limit characters are emitted without the specified string having been matched in full. xt is an xt which is executed when either the skipping emit capture test fails, where then it is passed false, or when the skipping emit capture test is successfully completed, where then it is passed true, unless it is set to 0, where then it is ignored.

add-ignore-capture

( b-addr bytes limit xt – )

This word adds an ignoring emit capture test, which fails if more than limit characters are emitted without having matched the specified string fully 0 or more times. xt is an xt which is executed when either the ignoring emit capture test fails, where then it is passed false, or when the ignoring emit capture test is successfully completed, where then it is passed true, unless it is set to 0, where then it is ignored.

Hardware Timers

zeptoforth on the RP2040 (i.e. the Raspberry Pi Pico) and the RP2350 (i.e. the Raspberry Pi Pico 2) has support for hardware timers and delays at up to a microsecond precision. Note that in practice microsecond precision is not necessarily possible, due to interrupts being disabled, interrupt priorities, busy-waits having a limited time resolution, and the chance of busy-waits being preempted if interrupts are not disabled during them.

The 64-bit microsecond timer can represent a sufficiently large range of values, i.e. it can represent thousands of years of time, such that it can be treated as effectively monotonic. Note that the user can change the value of the microsecond timer or pause it, but this is not recommended in most use cases.

The hardware timer on the RP2040 has one shared 64-bit microsecond counter and four “alarms” which are triggered by a set value to be compared with the lower 32 bits of the microsecond counter. The RP2350 is like the RP2040 in this regard except that it has a second identical hardare timer. Alarm handlers execute at interrupt time, so they must be interrupt-safe. Alarms must be enabled for each time they are used and are disabled when they are triggered. However, the interrupt state must be disabled before leaving the alarm interrupt handler or else they will be triggered repeatedly in an infinite loop. Also note that alarm handlers always execute on core 0 even when core 1 has been booted.

There are also busy-loop microsecond delays which wait until a given 64-bit microsecond time. Because the 64-bit microsecond counter can be reasonably treated as not wrapping, only a fixed 64-bit microsecond time is provided. On top of this, busy-loop microsecond delays which wait a given 64-bit microsecond interval are also available. This may be easier to use, but when waiting at repeated intervals maintaining a separate counter, incrementing it for each interval, and waiting until that time is likely to provide better behavior than waiting for intervals relative to the start of the wait.

The RP2350 also supports setting hardware timers to use the system clock for timing rather than the microsecond tick clock.

timer

The following words are in the timer module on the rp2040 and rp2350 platform:

us-counter-lsb

( – us )

Get the lower 32 bits in the current time in microseconds.

us-counter

( – us-d )

Get the current time in microseconds as a 64-bit value.

us-counter!

( us-d – )

Set the microsecond counter to a 64-bit value.

pause-us

( – )

Pause the microsecond counter.

unpause-us

( – )

Unpause the microsecond counter.

delay-until-us

( us-d – )

Delay until at least a 64-bit microsecond value, even though it may take longer considering the practical delay resolution, interrupts, and whether the microsecond counter is set or paused.

delay-us

( us-d – )

Delay a given number of microseconds, even though it may take longer considering the practical delay resolution, interrupts, and whether the microsecond counter is set or paused.

set-alarm

( us xt alarm – )

Set an alarm at a time. alarm is an alarm index from 0 to 3. xt is the execution token for the alarm handler. us is the lower 32 bits of the microsecond counter to trigger the alarm at.

clear-alarm

( alarm – )

Clear an alarm. alarm is an alarm index from 0 to 3.

clear-alarm-int

( alarm – )

Clear an alarm interrupt. alarm is an alarm index from 0 to 3. This must be called with the approriate alarm index inside an alarm handler for a given alarm or else the alarm handler will be called in an infinite loop.

alarm-set?

( alarm – set? )

Get whether an alarm is set.

x-out-of-range-alarm

Out of range alarm index exception.

The rp2350 platform also has the following words for controlling hardware clocks:

lock-timer

( – )

Lock a timer so it cannot be written to without a reset.

timer-locked?

( – locked? )

Get whether a timer is locked.

sysclk-timer

( – )

Set a timer to use the system clock as a source.

tick-timer

( – )

Set a timer to sue the microsecond tick clock as a source.

timer-sysclk?

( – sysclk? )

Get whether a timer is set to use the system clock as a source.

timer1

This module on the rp2350 only is identical to the timer module except that it controls a second hardware timer. It contains the same words as the timer module.

Task Queue Words

A task queue is a queue of waiting tasks, which then can be woken up, in the order of highest priority first and then the order of their joining the task queue, by another task. Note that tasks can wake up any given number of tasks before they join the task queue, upon which they will not actually deschedule themselves but rather increment the count of waiting tasks (which was negative in this case).

tqueue

The following words are in tqueue:

tqueue-size

( – bytes )

Get the size of a task queue in memory.

no-tqueue-limit

( – n )

Magic value indicating no task queue counter limit.

init-tqueue

( slock addr – )

Initialize a task queue with simple lock slock starting at the specified address; note that it must be tqueue-size bytes in size. It will have no counter limit, and its counter will be initialized to zero.

init-tqueue-full

( limit counter slock addr – )

Initialize a task queue with simple lock slock starting at the specified address; note that it must be tqueue-size bytes in size. Its counter limit will be initialized to limit and its counter will be initialized to counter.

wait-tqueue

( tqueue – )

Decrement the task queue’s internal wait counter. If it is negative, block the current task and place it in the task queue after the last task with a greater or equal priority. Note that the simple lock for the task queue must be held by the task which calls this; this simple lock is released if this blocks, to be claimed again when the task is readied.

wake-tqueue

( tqueue – )

Increment the task queue’s internal wait counter. If a counter limit is set, the internal wait counter will not increase beyond it. If there is a task in the task queue, ready the task with the highest priority added first to the task queue. Note that the simple lock for the task queue must be held by the task which calls this.

unwake-tqueue

( tqueue – )

Decrement the task queue’s internal wait counter.

wake-tqueue-all

( tqueue – )

Wake all the tasks waiting on a task queue.

Voltage words

There is support on the RP2040 and RP2350 for controlling the output voltage of the voltage regulator. The range of voltages normally supported is 850 mV to 1300 mV on the RP2040 and 550 mV to 1300 mV on the RP2350, but there is also an option to set an ‘unlimited’ voltage up to 3300 mV on the RP2350 at the risk of bricking your RP2350.

Warning: setting a voltage above 1300 mV on your RP2350 may brick it!

voltage

The voltage module contains the following words:

x-unsupported-voltage

( – )

This exception is raised if one attempts to set an out-of-range voltage. Note that attempting to set an in-range-voltage that is not one of the specific voltages supported will result in it getting rounded down a supported voltage.

voltage@

( – mvolts )

Get the current output voltage of the voltage regulator in millivolts.

set-voltage

( mvolts – )

Set the current output voltage of the voltage regulator in millivolts, from 850 mV to 1300 mV on the RP2040 and 550 mV to 1300 mV on the RP2350.

Attempting to set a voltage outside of one of these ranges will result in x-unsupported-voltage being raised. Attempting to set a voltage that is in one of these ranges which is not a specifically supported increment will result in it getting rounded down.

set-voltage-unlimited

( mvolts – )

Set the current output voltage of the voltage regulator in millivolts, from 850 mV to 1300 mV on the RP2040 and 550 mV to 3300 mV on the RP2350. Note that on the RP2040 this is merely an alias for set-voltage and has no differences from it, existing only for the sake of compatibility with the RP2350 codebase.

Attempting to set a voltage outside of one of these ranges will result in x-unsupported-voltage being raised. Attempting to set a voltage that is in one of these ranges which is not a specifically supported increment will result in it getting rounded down.

Warning: you may brick your RP2350 by using this word if you set a voltage above 1300 mV, so use it with caution!

Watchdog

The RP2040 includes watchdog functionality that, when enabled, triggers a reboot after a set delay during which the watchdog timer is not updated. It also has the capability to force a reset. By default the watchdog timer is disabled, the watchog delay is 1 second, and the watchdog (once enabled) is updated automatically each time the multitasker runs outside of a critical section. This behavior chan be changed in that the watchdog delay can be set to any time between 0 seconds (i.e. trigger immediately, and report a ‘force’ reboot reason rather than a ‘timer’ reason) and 16.777 seconds, and the multitasker can be set to not automatically update the watchdog timer (and this require manual updating by the user).

watchdog

x-out-of-range-watchdog-delay

( – )

Out of range watchdog delay exception.

update-watchdog

( – )

Update the watchdog timer with the currently set watchdog delay.

force-watchdog-reboot

( – )

Force an immediate watchdog reboot even if the watchdog timer is not enabled.

watchdog-delay-us!

( us – )

Set the watchdog delay to a specified positve number of microseconds, up to a delay of 8388607 microseconds. If an out of range delay is provided x-out-of-range-watchdog-delay will be raised. Note that if a value of 0 is provided and the watchdog is currently enabled the watchdog will trigger immediately and a ‘force’ reboot reason will be reported; this also will happen if the watchdog is disabled, and then the watchdog is enabled after this is called. Also note that if the watchdog is enabled and a value other than 0 is given the watchog timer will be updated with that value.

enable-watchdog

( – )

Enable the watchdog timer. If the watchdog delay is currently set to 0 the watchdog will trigger immediately and a ‘force’ reboot reason will be reported.

disable-watchdog

( – )

Disable the watchdog timer.

reboot-reason-watchdog-force?

( – force? )

Get whether the most recent reboot was due to a watchdog force.

reboot-reason-watchdog-timer?

( – timer? )

Get whether the most reason reboot was due to a watchdog timeout.

enable-multitasker-update-watchdog

( – )

Enable the multitasker automatically updating the watchdog timer each time it runs outside of a critical section.

disable-multitasker-update-watchdog

( – )

Disable the multitasker automatically updating the watchdog timer each time it runs outside of a critical section.

enable-fault-watchdog-reboot

( – )

Enable triggering a watchdog force reboot on a hardware fault.

disable-fault-watchdog-reboot

( – )

Disable triggering a watchdog force reboot on a hardware fault.

Wordlist Words

forth-wordlist

These words are in forth:

forth

( – wid )

Get the default wordlist, which is both a flash and a RAM wordlist.

internal

( – wid )

Get the internal wordlist, which includes both words defined in the kernel and words define outside the kernel

wordlist

( – wid )

Create a wordlist, a RAM wordlist (starting at 32768) if the current compilation mode is RAM mode, or a flash wordlist (starting at 1) if the current compilation mode is flash mode.

ram-wordlist

( – wid )

Create a RAM wordlist, regardless of the current compilation mode.

flash-wordlist

( – wid )

Create a flash wordlist, regardless of the current compilation mode.

set-current

( wid – )

Set the current compilation wordlist, into which new words will be added.

get-current

( – wid )

Get the current compilation wordlist.

set-order

( widn … wid1 u – )

Pop the new wordlist order size off the stack, then pop that number of wordlist IDs off the stack and set the wordlist order to them, with the wordlist ID closest to the top of the stack being the first wordlist in the wordlist order and the wordlist ID furthest from the top of the stack being the last wordlist in the wordlist order.

get-order

( – widn … wid1 u )

Push the wordlist order onto the stack, with the last wordlist ID in the order being furthest from the top of the stack and the first wordlist ID in the order being closest to the top of the stack, followed by pushing the wordlist order size onto the top of the stack.